<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The workes of Ephesus explained in a sermon before the honovrable House of Commons at their late solemne fast, April 27th 1642 / by Ioseph Caryl ...</title>
            <author>Caryl, Joseph, 1602-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35545</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C790</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3989</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12631459</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12631459</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64780</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35545)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64780)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 251:E147, no 14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The workes of Ephesus explained in a sermon before the honovrable House of Commons at their late solemne fast, April 27th 1642 / by Ioseph Caryl ...</title>
                  <author>Caryl, Joseph, 1602-1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Bartlet and William Bladen ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation II, 2-3.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64780:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64780:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE WORKES OF EPHESUS <hi>EXPLAINED</hi> IN A SERMON BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORE THE HONOVRABLE Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> at their late Solemne Faſt, <hi>April</hi> 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1642. By IOSEPH CARYL, <hi>Preacher</hi> to the Honourable Society of <hi>Lincolnes</hi> INNE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. SAM. 2. 30.</bibl> 
               <hi>Them that honour me, I will honour.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>MAT. 24. 46.</bibl> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is that ſervant, whom his Lord when he commeth, ſhall find ſo doing.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Iohn Bartlet</hi> and <hi>William Bladen,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Signe of the Guilt Cup, neare Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Gate. 1642.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64780:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64780:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE Houſe of <hi>COMMONS</hi> now aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Wo things mightily advance any Worke. A true Patterne, and a due Encouragement. I conceive there is no one Text in Holy Scripture, in which both are more cloſely, or more clearely laid together then in that, handled in the following Sermon. There, you have a Patterne for your Degrees in Working: Moſt caſes call you up to labour, and ſome to patience: There, you have a Patterne for the ſpeciall kindes of your worke: The removing of thoſe, both Things and Perſons, which you
<pb facs="tcp:64780:3"/> cannot but ſee are evill: The trying of thoſe which ſay they are, or are ſaid to be Good, and are not. There, you have a Patterne for the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of your Perſons with God in thoſe workes: The ſpiriting of them with Sincerity, and the crowning of them with Conſtancy. There, you have an encouragement unto all ſuch works: Ieſus Chriſt obſerves, and highly approves them All. Your Conſtancy and Sincerity, your Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Hypocriſie and removing of Impiety, The ſweat of your Labours and the exerciſe of your Patience are moſt pleaſing unto Him. Work by theſe Rules (Worthy Senators) and Peace ſhall be upon you, and upon the Engliſh-Iſrael of our God. It were very incongruous to detaine you long in the Suburbs of an Epiſtle, to whom (I feare) time can hardly be diſpenc'd to looke into the City. The unceſſant importunity of the Kingdomes worke tooke off ſome part of it, and obſcured others in the Delivery. Worke then preſſes the ſoule indeed, when it comes ſo faſt, that it ſhortens communion with God: A day with whom Faſting is infinitely better then a thouſand Feaſting-dayes, though with an <hi>Abaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erus.</hi> I have againe repaired thoſe breaches with <note place="margin">Heſt. 1.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:64780:3"/> the pen: and have ſent it ſomwhat fuller with this ſecond meſſage to your eyes, then it came with the firſt unto your eares. The Lord make way for it, both as heard and read, into all your hearts: and make you faithfull ever, in doing his worke, as he will be for ever more then Faithfull, Royall, in providing you and yours a reward. I will not interrupt your Great affaires in a Preamble, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then by reading, ſubſcrib'd,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſervant in the Faith of Chriſt, <hi>IOSEPH CARYLL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:64780:4"/>
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>Die Mercurij</hi> 27<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Aprilis</hi> 1642.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is this day ordered by the Houſe of Commons in Parliament, that M. <hi>Goodwyn,</hi> and M. <hi>Caryl</hi> ſhall be deſired to publiſh in Print the Sermons they preached at the Faſt, before the Houſe of Commons. And it is further ordered, that none ſhall preſume to print them for the ſpace of two Moneths, but ſuch as they ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſinge, Cler. Parl. de Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="order_to_print">
            <p>I Appoint <hi>Iohn Bartlet,</hi> and <hi>William Bladen</hi> to print my Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOSEPH CARYL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata:</head>
            <p>Pag. 5. lin. 1. nine, <hi>read</hi> ninth, p. 16. l. 5. her, <hi>r.</hi> you, l. 15. <hi>r.</hi> the comma after alſo. p. 43. l. 16. carkaſſe, <hi>r.</hi> carkaſſes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64780:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED At the late FAST before the Commons Houſe of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>REV. 2. v. 2, 3.</bibl>
                  <p>I know thy works, and thy labour and thy patience, and how thou canſt not beare them which are evill, and haſt tryed them which ſay they are Apostles and are not, and haſt found them lyars.</p>
                  <p>And haſt borne and haſt patience, and for my name ſake haſt laboured and hast not fainted.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat ancient Character of this Book <hi>(quot verba tot Sacramenta) as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hier. in praef ad Bib.</note> 
               <hi>myſteries as words,</hi> like <hi>that flaming Sword</hi> in the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. of <hi>Geneſis</hi> which ſtopt the way to the <hi>tree of life,</hi> may here ſeeme to ſtoppe the way to this Tree of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Time hath alwayes proved the ſureſt Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64780:5"/> of a Prophecy, and the event expounds more in one day, then the Comment of many Ages. Yet as the greateſt Rivers, ſo the moſt myſterious bookes of Scripture runne not in the ſame continued depth: Though in ſome places they can ſcarce be ſounded, yet in others they ſhew their bottome and may be waded.</p>
            <p>This is evident (as in others, ſo) <hi>in this Booke of Revelation,</hi> moſt of whoſe Truthes (as ſome have ſaid of all truth) <hi>lie in a deepe pit;</hi> yet even here we may ſometime diſcover truth in the ſuperficies of the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; even here are many plaine Doctrines, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall obſervations. Such the Text now read holds forth unto us; about ſuch (waving all Quaeries con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Prophecy) I intend (Honourable and Beloved) through the <hi>aſsiſtance of Chriſt</hi> and your <hi>Chriſtian patience,</hi> to ſpeake at this time, not unſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly (I hope) to this great preſence and ſolemne oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
            <p>The words are part of that Epiſtle written to the Angell of the Church of <hi>Epheſus;</hi> and with him to the whole body of that Church, and in them to all Chriſtian Churches, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>He that hath an eare to heare, let him heare what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches. Integris igitur Eccleſias haec ſcribuntur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paraeus,</hi> and <hi>whatſoever things were written aforetime, were wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Par. in loc.</hi> Rom. 15. 4</note> 
               <hi>for our learning,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. I need not therefore trouble my ſelf about a paralell. It is enough that the common ſence and abſtracted conſtruction of this Scripture, is very applyable both to <hi>the buſineſſe</hi> of this day, and to the <hi>buſineſses</hi> of theſe (if ever any) <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text containes in Generall, <hi>the Obſervation</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64780:5"/> 
               <hi>which Christ tooke of, the Approbation which Christ gave unto the workes of that Church:</hi> in and about which workes, Chriſt obſerves and approves three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a double Gradation. 1. <hi>Labour.</hi> 2. <hi>Patience.</hi> Some in working doe not labour, and moſt in labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring are not put to the uſe of patience; in theſe works of theirs both are joyned, the paines of labour, and the exerciſe of patience.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Chriſt obſerves and approves a double Specification of theſe workes, or what theſe workes were. 1. The removall of thoſe who were apparantly naught, <hi>Thou canſt not beare them which are evill.</hi> 2. The Tryall of thoſe who had an appearance of being good. <hi>Thou haſt tryed them which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not, and hast ſound them lyars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Chriſt obſerves and approves a double qualification of theſe workes. 1. The ſincerity and uprightneſſe of them, <hi>Thou haſt borne and haſt pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and haſt laboured.</hi> Why? not to make thy ſelf great, or thy name glorious, but, <hi>for my names ſake.</hi> 2. The Conſtancy, courage and unweariedneſſe of them, thou haſt done all this, and yet <hi>thou haſt not fainted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the Obſervation which Chriſt takes of their works in generall, <hi>I know thy workes.</hi> To whom this <hi>(I)</hi> relates we may read in the former verſe. <hi>Theſe things ſaith he that holdeth the ſeven ſtarrs in his right hand, who walketh in the midſt of the ſeven gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den candlesticks.</hi> A deſcription which fits none but him, to whom <hi>all power in heaven and in earth is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, Ieſus Chriſt, God and man; I know.</hi> There is a twofold knowledge, firſt, <hi>ſimple.</hi> 2. <hi>Mixt. Simple</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64780:6"/> 
               <hi>knowledge</hi> is the bare apprehenſion of the object, what it is. <hi>Mixt knowledge</hi> is that which carries along with it either <hi>pleaſure</hi> or <hi>diſlike,</hi> according as the object is, we apprehend. <hi>(Thy workes)</hi> Workes are of two ſorts, <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Bad,</hi> and in reference to either: workes are taken ſomtime <hi>ſtrictly</hi> as oppoſed to words, as oppoſed to thoughts: Sometime more <hi>largely,</hi> and ſo our words come in account among our works, and ſo our very thoughts are works; yea in a large ſence, even things not done, nor ſpoken, nor thought may be numbred among our workes.</p>
            <p>To abſtaine from evill is a worke of grace, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit good is a worke of ſinne, not to doe our duty is a worke of darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>larger ſence</hi> take works in the Text. <hi>Good works</hi> are expreſſed here in theſe two verſes: and <hi>ſome evill,</hi> the decay of their <hi>firſt love,</hi> and the conſequent of it, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from their <hi>firſt workes</hi> in the two following, where he is plaine with them, <hi>I have ſomewhat againſt thee;</hi> he reckons up their faults too, and in refernce to both pronounceth, <hi>I know thy workes,</hi> I clearly apprehend all; what are good I know and approve, what are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill I know and diſlike. Hence obſerve,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That all the workes of men lie open to the ſight of</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Chriſt who is God and Man.</hi> Be they good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, be they actions, words or thoughts, be they ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinences from evill, or omiſſions of good, they all fall within the proſpect of Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>The wayes of a man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) are before the Lord, and he pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 5. 21.</note> 
               <hi>or weigheth as in a ballance all his wayes.</hi> If they be but halfe a graine to light, his beame <note place="margin">Pro. 15 3.</note> will diſcover it. <hi>The eyes of the Lord are in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place beholding the evill and the good.</hi> The hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64780:6"/> thirty nine <hi>Pſalme</hi> is but a continued Paraphraſe upon this point, <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>O Lord thou hast ſearched me and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ 139. 1. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>known me,</hi> Men often ſearch men and yet cannot know them. There are ſecrets and depths in man which man cannot reach: <hi>What man knoweth the things of man, ſave</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 11.</note> 
               <hi>the ſpirit of man which is in him?</hi> But the Spirit of Chriſt knoweth what is in any man, better then any mans own ſpirit. <hi>He</hi> hath a thred which will lead him into all, and thorough all the <hi>Labirynths</hi> and turnings of the moſt <hi>Matchavilian ſpirit.</hi> He hath a light which will diſcover in man the <hi>very depths of Satan,</hi> v. 24. <hi>Thou haſt ſearched and knowne me, Me,</hi> not only <hi>Me</hi> naturall (of which hee ſpeakes, verſ. 15, 16. <hi>My ſubſtance was not hid from thee, when I was made in ſecret, thine eyes did ſee my ſubſtance yet being imperfect and in thy Booke were all my members written)</hi> but alſo <hi>Mee</hi> civill and <hi>Mee</hi> morall, as it is expounded, verſe 2, 3. <hi>Thou knoweſt my downe ſitting and my upri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> (thou art at both ends of all my workes) <hi>thou compaſſeſt or winnowest my path</hi> (if there bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny chaffe or traſh thou wilt make it fly) <hi>and art acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all my waies.</hi> He finds <hi>God</hi> not only at his <hi>fingers ends,</hi> but at his <hi>tongues end too, v.</hi> 4. <hi>There is not a word in my tongue, but loe ô Lord thou knoweſt it altogether.</hi> His knowledge ſtaieth not here in the <hi>porch or lobbies,</hi> but paſſeth into the <hi>preſence,</hi> yea into the <hi>privy chamber, v.</hi> 2 <hi>thou underſtandeſt my thoughts,</hi> and not only <hi>thoughts pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> but thoſe which are in <hi>poſse</hi> and to come, <hi>thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my thoughts,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>afarre off,</hi> that is before I thought them. Things before they be, are known to him, by whom all things have their being. <hi>Who knows</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon, Pr.</hi> 27. 1.) <hi>what a day may bring forth? man</hi> knows not what is in <hi>the womb</hi> of the next day, we cannot
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64780:7"/> ſee (unerringly) <hi>an houre before us.</hi> But Chriſt knows what lies in the <hi>Wombe of eternity,</hi> he knowes what all ages ſhall bring forth, he can ſee <hi>thouſands of years</hi> before him. <hi>He declares the end from the beginning and from ancient times the things that are not yet done.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſ 46. 10 Heb. 4. 13.</note> 
               <hi>All things,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle (whether paſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or to come) <hi>are naked and open to the eyes of him with whom we have to doe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, both elegant Metaphors and implying thus much, that as the outward <hi>proportion and lineaments</hi> of the body are diſtinctly ſeene. When that is <hi>naked</hi> and <hi>uncloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed,</hi> that as the bowels and internals are perfectly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned when the body is diſſected, even ſo are we, and all we doe, and all that ſhall be done before the Lord.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Sea of Glaſſe like Chryſtall</hi> (Revel. 4. 6.) <hi>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding before the Throne</hi> is well expounded to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the whole world with the confluence and ſeries of all things therin: The World is like <hi>the Sea,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſo <hi>tempeſtuous, up</hi> and <hi>downe, ebbing</hi> or <hi>flowing</hi> ever; but it is called a <hi>Sea of Glaſſe like chryſtall,</hi> to note that Chriſt doth not onely looke upon it, <hi>but through it,</hi> it is to him, <hi>corpus diaphanum,</hi> a cleare and <hi>tranſparent body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are foure <hi>motions</hi> very neceſſary to be made <note place="margin">Firſt part of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication in regard of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent duty.</note> in regard of this daies dutie, <hi>Prayer and Faſting;</hi> the Doctrine in hand joynes ſtrongly with me in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of them all.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>the duty of this day</hi> moves us to <hi>Selfe-ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> and <hi>Selfe examination.</hi> The voyce of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſounds like that voyce of the Prophet <hi>Ieremy, Let us ſearch and try our wayes:</hi> Like that voyce of <note place="margin">Lam 3. 40. Zeph. 2. 1.</note> the Prophet <hi>Zephany, Gather your ſelves together,</hi> or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64780:7"/> as others render it, <hi>Fanne your ſelves,</hi> yea <hi>Fanne your ſelves ô Nation not deſired.</hi> This is a day wherein every worke is called to the <hi>touch-ſtone,</hi> to try their metall, and all our <hi>wayes</hi> to the <hi>ballance, even the ballance of the Sanctuary,</hi> that wee may know their weight. The Doctrine cals as <hi>loud</hi> for this alſo. For doth Chriſt know our works, and ſhall we be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of them? Doth he travell into our hearts, and ſhall our hearts be <hi>terra incognita</hi> unto us? Shal we be ſtrangers at home? <hi>A ſinne of Ignorance</hi> is leſſe then <hi>a ſinne of Knowledge,</hi> but to be ignorant of thoſe ſinnes we may know, for the enquiry, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes and heightens them. <hi>Paul</hi> in one caſe after he had ſearched, ſaid, <hi>I know nothing by my ſelfe, yet</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4 4</note> 
               <hi>am I not hereby juſtified:</hi> but if we know nothing by our ſelves, becauſe vve vvill not be at the pains to ſearch, vve ſhall hereby be condemned; both becauſe the beſt have many ſinnes <hi>they may know,</hi> and becauſe to all their ſinnes they have added this, the not <hi>endeavouring to know them.</hi> The <hi>Heathens</hi> ſay, that Oracle of theirs came downe from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Noſce teipſum, know thy ſelfe;</hi> I am ſure no Chriſtian can aſcend to Heaven, <hi>unleſſe he know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:</hi> Unleſſe he both know himſelfe to be a ſinner, and deſire to know (according to his light) in what he hath ſinned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>duty of this day</hi> moves us <hi>to the free, full and ſincere confeſſion of ſinne,</hi> vvhich is <hi>the putting of our ſelves into the hands of Iuſtice, in hope of mercy.</hi> This is one of <hi>the eſſentials in a Faſt,</hi> and vve finde a <hi>fourth part of the day</hi> allovved to it in <note place="margin">Neh 9. 3.</note> the 9. of <hi>Nehemiah.</hi> The Doctrine moves as ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for confeſſion as this daies duty can. What more
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64780:8"/> prevailing Argument to <hi>confeſſe</hi> our ſinnes unto God then this, that we cannot <hi>conceale</hi> our ſinnes from God. God cals for <hi>confeſſion,</hi> but not for <hi>information.</hi> Why doe we make ſuch <hi>long Narratives</hi> in Prayer? Why doe we <hi>tell the ſtory of our ſinfull lives</hi> in the eares of God? What, is it to teach or inſtruct the Almighty? O no, God knowes our ſinnes enough to <hi>puniſh them,</hi> though we doe not confeſſe them: but he will never know them, ſo as to <hi>pardon them,</hi> unleſſe we confeſſe them. Take then that excellent counſell of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, <hi>Fac confitendo propitium, quem tacendo non facis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. To.</hi> 8. <hi>in</hi> Pſ. 74.</note> 
               <hi>neſcium,</hi> make him willing to pardon thy ſinne by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, whom thou doeſt not make unknowing of thy ſinne by concealing: For though thou ſitteſt as cloſe this day upon the <hi>Idols of thy heart, and the evils of thy way, as</hi> Rachel <hi>did upon her Fathers Images,</hi> yet thou doeſt not hide thy ſinne from God, but the mercies of God from thy ſin.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the duty of this day cals us to Self abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and bluſhing, to ſhame and confuſion of face be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord. Thus <hi>Ezra</hi> in the day of his mourning cryes out, <hi>O my God I am aſhamed, and bluſh to lift up</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezr. 9. 6.</note> 
               <hi>my face to thee.</hi> So <hi>Daniel</hi> in his Faſt, <hi>O Lord to us belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dan. 9. 8.</note> 
               <hi>confuſion of face;</hi> that is, (as I conceive) we have great reaſon to be aſhamed and bluſh: For thoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall tinctures of the face, the white and the red are ſo confounded in a bluſh, that while it laſts no man can diſtinguiſh the Complexion. The preſent doctrine cals us to this <hi>gracefull ſhame, and becomming confuſion of face.</hi> Shame ariſeth two wayes, firſt from the doing of ſomewhat againſt <hi>common light,</hi> and <hi>ordinary Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi> Secondly from an apprehenſion that what we have done, <hi>is knowne.</hi> The very ſight of a man, who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64780:8"/> (to our knowledge) knowes ſuch a thing by us, fetches <hi>a bluſh from bare ingenuity.</hi> How ſhould this make us aſhamed this day, while we conſider our ſelves in his preſence, who knowes every ſinne of our Lives, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our whole Lives to be a ſin: Who knowes all the errour of our works, or rather all our works to be an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: Who knowes the lightneſſe and vanity of all our wayes, or rather all our wayes to be but lightneſſe and vanity. Any, but a <hi>whores forehead,</hi> a forehead ſteeled with impudence, will be aſhamed of ſuch works as theſe, when we heare God knowes them: For none can heare and beleeve, and not be aſhamed. O let not the <hi>ſhew of our countenance witneſſe againſt us</hi> (as it did <note place="margin">Iſa. 3. 9.</note> againſt thoſe Jewes) that we have this day declared our ſinne as <hi>Sodome.</hi> If we be not <hi>aſhamed,</hi> it will; there was no <hi>ſhew of ſhame</hi> in their countenance, and that was to declare like <hi>Sodome.</hi> To confeſſe ſinne in the ſight of God, and not be aſhamed, is an act of <hi>impudence not of repentance.</hi> It is better to hide our ſinnes for ſhame, then not to be aſhamed of them, when they are not hid. O let the <hi>ſhew of our countenance witneſſe for us,</hi> that we have this day declared our ſinnes <hi>as Sion,</hi> as <hi>the mourners in Sion.</hi> Let us be aſhamed, that we may <hi>never be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, this duty bids us be very cautious and watchfull. When we come to be humbled for all our <hi>old ſinnes,</hi> we had need take heed we doe not <hi>renew our ſinnes,</hi> and make <hi>debts</hi> while we come to get <hi>diſcharges.</hi> Our miſcarriages in this duty may be ſuch as will <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God,</hi> while we come to <hi>pacific him,</hi> and <hi>faſten</hi> thoſe judgements upon the Kingdomes, which we are ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to <hi>remove.</hi> As therefore we are called to the duty
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64780:9"/> of faſting, ſo the duty cals to us, <hi>take heed how ye faſt.</hi> This motion the Doctrine brings alſo, and cryes with <hi>a mighty voice, take heed how ye faſt.</hi> Why? Faſting and Prayer <hi>are a worke, I, ſtrong worke, ſpirituall worke.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt who knowes all <hi>our works,</hi> knowes theſe <hi>above all.</hi> In a ſence, all our Services in reference to God are eye-ſervices; but on this ſervice his eye is fixed, <note place="margin">1 King. 8. 29. Mat. 18. 20.</note> as it was prayed about the Temple, <hi>Let thine eyes be open toward this houſe night and day. Where two or three are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in my name, there am I in the midſt of them.</hi> To be in the <hi>midſt,</hi> notes a <hi>Speciall preſence.</hi> I will not onely ſtand at the <hi>doore,</hi> and looke in; but I will come in amongſt you, and into the <hi>midſt of you,</hi> to take a view what all doe, of all your Services: as well as to take delight in, and give aſſiſtance to, or concurrence with my faithfull Servants. In the two and twentieth of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>That the King came in to the Feaſt to ſee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>the guests.</hi> And there quickly <hi>eſpyed out a man,</hi> a ſingle perſon (though but one, he could not eſcape in the throng unſeen) <hi>that had not on a wedding garment.</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſt that King is come this day to the Faſt, to ſee his mourners, and he will quickly eſpye every man in this Congregation, that hath not on him a mourning garment, that hath not in him a mourning heart. He knowes when it is a Faſt and when not, when it is his Faſt, and when it is our Faſt. As he queſtions, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upbraides the Jewes, <hi>did ye at all faſt unto me, even</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Zach. 7. 5.</note> 
               <hi>to me?</hi> As here he diſcovers it none of <hi>his Faſt,</hi> by a failing in the end. So in the 58. Chapter of <hi>Eſay,</hi> he diſcovers it to be none of his Faſt by their failing in the <hi>manner, Is it ſuch a Faſt that I have choſen?</hi> He knowes <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 5.</note> when we are but <hi>as a people</hi> that ſeeke, and when we ſeek
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64780:9"/> 
               <hi>indeed.</hi> When we onely <hi>act a part, and perſonate</hi> a holy Praying, Faſting, humbled people, and when we are really ſuch. He knowes whether we are come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the <hi>Order and Law of our owne hearts,</hi> or only by the <hi>Law and Order of the State.</hi> He knowes when we make a <hi>worke of Faſting,</hi> and when but onely a <hi>talke of Faſting.</hi> But when is Faſting a worke? you may learne that in the Faſt of <hi>Niniveh:</hi> In the cloſe of which it is <note place="margin">Ion. 3. 10.</note> ſaid, that the <hi>Lord ſaw their works.</hi> And what were their <hi>Faſt-works?</hi> It is added by way of expoſition in the next words, <hi>The Lord ſaw their workes, that they turned from their evill wayes.</hi> Unleſſe God ſees <hi>turning from our ſinnes</hi> in a Faſt, he ſees no worke in a Faſt; It is not <hi>talking of ſin,</hi> nor <hi>talking againſt ſinne,</hi> but <hi>turning from ſinne,</hi> that is the worke. This muſt be the <hi>reſult</hi> of all; Abſtinence, Prayer, Preaching, Hearing, Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Mourning, muſt all be reſolved into <hi>turning</hi> from our evill wayes, Without this God ſees <hi>no worke</hi> in Faſting, but the <hi>worke of hypocriſie,</hi> and ſuch can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no wages but the <hi>wages of hypocrites,</hi> to have their praying and weeping, and teares here, rewarded with weeping and wayling, and gnaſhing of teeth for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>So farre of the point as it may be applyed to the workes of this <hi>Speciall Duty.</hi> Now for workes in <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it convinces thoſe who thinke of <hi>drawing a Curtaine,</hi> and <hi>ſpreading a vayle of darkneſse</hi> betweene Chriſt and their workes. Some while they doe things not <hi>fit to be ſeen,</hi> would willingly perſwade themſelves, they are not <hi>ſeen in doing them.</hi> Thus the proud, ſubtle, mercileſſe oppreſſor is deſcribed in the tenth Pſalme.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64780:10"/> 
               <hi>He hath ſaid in his heart, God hath forgotten, he hideth his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 10. 11.</note> 
               <hi>face and will never ſee it.</hi> The ſame ſort of men (a ſort of men as bad within a degree as bad can be) are brought in under the ſame Notion of Atheiſme, In the 94<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Pſalme. <hi>They breake in peeces, O Lord, thy people,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 94. 5, 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>and afflect thy heritage, they ſlay the widow and the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and murther the fatherleſſe; yet they ſay</hi> (v. 7.) <hi>the Lord ſhall not ſee, neither ſhall the God of</hi> Iacob <hi>regard it.</hi> Others perhaps have not <hi>made out this heart ſecuring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion;</hi> yet with thoſe in <hi>Iob,</hi> they <hi>argue</hi> and <hi>debate</hi> it. <note place="margin">Iob 22. 13</note> 
               <hi>How doth God know? can he judge through the darke Cloud?</hi> You may reade theſe <hi>Queriſts reſolved</hi> in the next words; <hi>Thicke Clouds are a covering to him that he cannot ſee.</hi> He that vvill let his heart <hi>dally</hi> awhile about <hi>blaſphemous Questions,</hi> may quickly be ſetled in <hi>blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Concluſions.</hi> But let all ſuch, whether queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning or reſolving, heare themſelves fully and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confuted by the Pſalmiſt in the place afore quoted: <note place="margin">Pſal. 94. 8, 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>Vnderſtand ye brutiſh among the people, and ye fooles when will ye be wiſe? He that planted the eare, ſhall not he heare? He that formed the eye, ſhall not he ſee? He that teacheth man knowledge, ſhall not he know? The Lord knoweth the thoughts of man that they are vaine;</hi> and this the vaineſt thought of all, That God knowes not their thoughts. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw him who <hi>is inviſible.</hi> Doe not thinke that <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 27</note> he who is <hi>inviſible</hi> cannot ſee. God like the <hi>Opticke virtue</hi> in the eye, ſees all, and is ſeen of none. No man needs a <hi>window</hi> in his breaſt (as 'tis ſaid the Heathen <hi>Momus</hi> wiſh) for God to looke in at, every man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>God</hi> is all <hi>Window. There is no darkneſſe</hi> (faith <hi>Elihu) nor ſhadow of death, where the workers of wickedneſſe may</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 34. 22.</note> 
               <hi>hide themſelves.</hi> No naturall darkneſſe, no artificiall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64780:10"/> darkneſſe, no duſt raiſed, or miſt ſcattered by Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians can hide them. The eyes of Chriſt are <hi>as a flame</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1. 14.</note> 
               <hi>of fire;</hi> and the Schoole of Nature teacheth us, that the <hi>fiery eye</hi> needs no outward light, that ſees <hi>(extra mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo)</hi> by ſending out a ray, and by the ſame ray which apprehends the Object, doth alſo enlighten the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, or paſſage to it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this may be for <hi>Admonition.</hi> To lay a mighty reſtraint upon our Spirits, and keep us from every evill worke. It was an adviſe of the Moraliſt to his Schollers, that they ſhould ever carry in their eye a conceived repreſentation of ſome <hi>ſevere Cato,</hi> or <hi>Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Ariſtarch,</hi> as the Overſeer and cenſurer of all their actions. That, he thought, would hold them in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe. God ſeemes to ſpeake the ſame Counſell, and almoſt the ſame Language to <hi>Abraham: Walke before</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17. 1.</note> 
               <hi>me, and be thou perfect.</hi> The eye of Conſcience reſtraines much, it is hard for a man to ſin under the eye of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: What then is the eye of God? who is <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then Conſcience, and knoweth all things.</hi> Could we as <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3. 20. Pſ. 16. 8. Acts 2. 25.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes (in the type) of Chriſt, <hi>ſet the Lord al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes before us:</hi> Or as the Apoſtle quotes it, <hi>could we foreſee the Lord alwayes before our face,</hi> we ſhould not be ſo often, ſo eaſily moved by temptations as we are. And as this ſhould caution all men in all works: ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe who are actively concerned in works of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. In theſe, as Chriſt hath a more <hi>ſpeciall Intereſt</hi> (all power being put into his hand, and from him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated unto man) ſo upon theſe he hath a more <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Eye. God ſtandeth in the Congregation of the mighty,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 82. 1.</note> 
               <hi>he judgeth among the gods;</hi> Not alwayes by conſenting, for they may erre and judge unjuſtly, <hi>v.</hi> 2. And Chriſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64780:11"/> will never vote with ſuch; but he alwayes judgeth by diſcerning whether the ſentence be juſt or not. <hi>Iehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> warnes his Iudges upon this very ground, <hi>Take</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chr. 19. 6</note> 
               <hi>heed what ye doe, for ye judge not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the judgement;</hi> as if he had ſaid, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ride circuit with you to all places, or fit with you in all your Conſultations; but the Lord can and doth, he is with you in the Iudgement. With you, not onely by way of aſſiſtance, and protection (as that phraſe often imports) but alſo by way of notice-taking, and obſervation. Hee keepes a record of every judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and will at laſt judge them all over a ſecond time.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Doctrine carries wrath and terrour in it, againſt all evill-workers. <hi>Woe to them that ſeeke deepe to hide their counſell from the Lord, and their works are in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſ. 29. 15.</note> 
               <hi>the darke, and they ſay, who ſeeth us? and who knoweth us?</hi> And why woe to theſe? The Pſalmiſt tels us why, arguing the certainty of revenges upon this ground: <hi>Thou Lord haſt ſeen it for thou beholdeſt miſchiefe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 10. 13, 14</note> 
               <hi>and ſpite, to requite it with thy hand;</hi> though no eye of man or Angell ſees it, yet thine doth. And therefore though no hand of man or Angell requite it, yet thou wilt requite it with <hi>thy hand. Surely I have ſeen yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the bloud of</hi> Naboth (Murder ever bleeds freſh in the eye of God, to him many yeares, yea that eternity which is paſt, is but yeſterday.) <hi>Surely I have ſeen yeſterday the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 King 9. 26.</note> 
               <hi>bloud of</hi> Naboth, <hi>and the bloud of his ſonnes, ſaith the Lord, and I will requite thee in this plat, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Bloud ſhall ſurely enough be requited with bloud, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſurely the Lord hath ſeen it. <hi>That which a man ſowes the ſame alſo ſhall he reape; he that ſoweth to the fleſh ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 7, 8.</note>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64780:11"/> 
               <hi>of the fleſh reape corruption.</hi> And why? the reaſon is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated in the beginning of the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. verſe, <hi>God is not mocked;</hi> you cannot cozen him with <hi>tares,</hi> and <hi>Cockle</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Wheate;</hi> All our workes done are as ſeed under ground, ſuch as we caſt in ſuch will the crop be at harveſt: Never better for the kind: alwayes worſe for the degree, time ripens ſinne and improves the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; <hi>They have ſowne the winde, and ſhall reape the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ 8. 7.</note> 
               <hi>whirlewinde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, this ſerves for our <hi>comfort and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in good workes</hi> 3. wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if God knowes them, then they ſhall not be loſt in the <hi>darkneſse of Secrecy.</hi> The counſell of Chriſt is, <hi>when thou doeſt thine almes, doe not ſound a Trumpet,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> 
               <hi>when thou prayeſt enter into thy cloſet, when thou faſteſt appeare not unto men to faſt.</hi> And leaſt any ſhould be diſcouraged, he as often ſubjoynes, <hi>your Father ſeeth in ſecret.</hi> When the <hi>left hand knowes not what the right hand doth,</hi> God knowes what the right hand doth; he is nearer to us, then we are to our ſelves. But although <hi>our light</hi> (as Chriſt alſo adviſeth) <hi>ſhines ſo before men, that they may ſee our good workes;</hi> yet many men will <note place="margin">Mat 5. 16.</note> ſend them to the <hi>Land of darkneſse, where all things are forgotten;</hi> often burying the workes, while they who wrought them are alive. It is too uſuall to write the faults of others in braſſe, and their nobleſt undertakings and ſucceſſes in the water or on the ſand: Such is mans unrighteouſneſſe. But the point yeelds comfort ſtill; No good worke ſhall be loſt in the darkneſſe of oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>For God is not unrighteous to forget your worke and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 10.</note> 
               <hi>labour of love, which ye have ſhewed to his Name. Our workes come up for a memoriall before God,</hi> and are regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred <note place="margin">Act. 10. 4.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64780:12"/> in Heaven for ever: Yea or many workes (in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pight of envy) he ſaith (as of the womans anointing him.) <hi>Whereſoever this Goſpell ſhall be preached in the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat 26. 13</note> 
               <hi>whole world, there ſhall alſo this that you have done be told for a memoriall of her.</hi> He hath and will anſwer the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of every <hi>Nehemiah, Remember me, O my God, concerning</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Neh 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>this, and wipe not out my good deeds that I have done for the houſe of my God, and for the offices thereof?</hi> Yet further, though we our ſelves ſhould doe much good which we doe not know (for there are as ſinnes, ſo (in a ſence) good workes of ignorance) or if we our ſelves ſhould not remember the good which we doe knowingly (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of himſelfe, <hi>I forget that which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 13.</note> yet the Lord will at the laſt redeeme our workes out of this darkneſſe, alſo the darkneſſe, both of our owne ignorance and forgetfulneſſe. <hi>When ſaw we thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 37, 38.</note> 
               <hi>hungred, and fed thee? or thirſty and gave thee drinke? when ſaw we thee naked, and cloathed thee? or a stranger, and tooke thee in?</hi> It ſeemes theſe were ſtrangers to their owne Acts, either not underſtanding, or not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring what they had done, Chriſt therefore expounds and remembers for them: <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 40.</note> 
               <hi>as ye have done it unto one of the leaſt of theſe my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ye have done it unto me.</hi> Neither ſecrecy, nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulneſſe, nor ignorance, our owne or others, can long cover a good worke. Let it be our care onely to doe good, it is the care of Chriſt to record the good which we have done.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that Chriſt knowes our workes hath this comfort in it, <hi>Then they are rightly underſtood.</hi> There was never any <hi>great thing</hi> done in the world, but it fell under <hi>miſconſtruction.</hi> And often ſuch <hi>gloſſes</hi> are given
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64780:12"/> as doe corrupt the Contexture of ſincereſt workes: For the concluſions of malice are ever like thoſe of Logick, following <hi>(partem deteriorem)</hi> the worſer and weaker part, if it can but ſnatch a ſhadow, or ſhape a ſurmiſe of either. How often are works of holineſſe interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hypocriſie? and the works of zeale vaine-glory? How often is contending for the faith miſ-called facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? <note place="margin">Iud. 3.</note> and contending againſt ſuperſtition, humour? In the midſt of all theſe clamours and loades of ſlander, this may beare up our hearts, God knowes our workes. And though now ignorance and malice ſit upon and cenſure our workes, yet God will put them forth (at one time or other) with the Comment of our owne honeſt meanings upon them: Not tortured and wire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne with falſe expoſitions of an adverſary. <hi>He will</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 37. 6.</note> 
               <hi>bring forth our righteouſneſse as the light, and our juſt dealing as the Noone day.</hi> This quieted <hi>Iobs</hi> Spirit in the midſt of all the miſ-apprehenſions of his friends, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 16. 19.</note> 
               <hi>my witneſse is in Heaven, and my record is on High.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſeeing God knowes our workes, they ſhall certainly be rewarded. It is one of the <hi>vanities</hi> which <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerved under the Sunne (and it is a vexing <note place="margin">Eccl. 4. 4.</note> vanity) <hi>That for every good worke a man is envied of his neighbour.</hi> But will it not ballance this vanity, that for every right worke a man ſhall be honoured and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of his God? Thoſe workes which the world en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaines with Scorne, and beſmeares with Calumny, Chriſt who knowes them will entertaine with an <hi>Euge,</hi> and reward with Glory, <hi>Well done good and faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> 
               <hi>enter into thy Maſters joy.</hi> Man doth, yea he ought to doe many good works, which are never knowne of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64780:13"/> man. And thoſe which are knowne, come uſually but to an ill market; at the beſt it were ſcarce worth the while, to doe good, if all the pay were to be expected from the hands of men: But as we can doe no good work, but it is knowne to God, ſo becauſe it is known it ſhall be repayed: <hi>Blow not a Trumpet</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>your</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Father ſees in ſecret;</hi> And obſerve what is three times inferred upon that, <hi>Your Father which ſees in ſecret, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">V. 4 6, 18.</note> 
               <hi>will reward you openly;</hi> himſelfe will doe it, he will not ſend his Steward. And becauſe many ſay <hi>(non tua ſed te)</hi> Lord let us have thee rather then thine; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will not onely reward ſuch himſelfe, but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe will be their reward: And O, how exceeding <note place="margin">Gen. 15. 1.</note> great, how exceeding all greatneſſe is that reward, which hath no meaſure but infiniteneſſe. I, ſo watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is Chriſt over the leaſt graine of good we doe, that he hath proteſted a cup of cold water (almoſt an indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable charity) given to a Diſciple of his, in his name, <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 42</note> ſhall in no wiſe (there is a double negative for it) loſe a reward. Water is a ſmall curteſie, and cold water a leſſe; yet though thus given, as prepared by nature onely, without the leaſt charge to heate or mixe it, it cannot miſſe a reward. And if workes of Love which coſt us nothing ſhall be thus rewarded, what ſhall we be repayed for thoſe, in which (like <hi>Araunab</hi> to <hi>David) As Kings we give unto the King?</hi> When we are royall and magnificent for Chriſt, When we ſpare no coſt, <note place="margin">1 Sam. 24. 23.</note> nor ſticke at any price to ſerve Chriſt and his Church, or Chriſt in his Church. If we ſhal be rewarded thus for cold water from the ſpring, which can hardly be called ours, what ſhall we be for warm water, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our browes &amp; bodies given to a diſciple in Chriſts name. If we ſhall be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64780:13"/> thus rewarded for water, what ſhall we be for our bloud ſhed for the name of Chriſt. When for Chriſts ſake we labour and ſweat, and dye to do good for others. When to Chriſt and to his people in his name, we give our time, and our ſtrength, our ſleep and our meats, our comforts and recreations, our credit and our eſtates, our liberties and our lives. When <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> read in <note place="margin">Heſt. 6. 1, 2, 3.</note> the booke of the Records of the <hi>Chronicles,</hi> how <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai</hi> had diſcovered a treaſon againſt his perſon. The King enquires <hi>what honour and what dignity hath bin done unto</hi> Mordecai <hi>for this?</hi> It ſeemes if the King had thought on, or read him ſooner, he had rewarded him ſooner. God hath ever in his eye all the Records and Chronicles of your good workes, he reades your jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals every day, and when he meets with any that have done or ſpoken aright for him, he enquires what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, what dignity hath been done for this man? If none hath been done, he will doe it himſelfe, if any thing hath been done, he will doe yet more: <hi>He that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 30.</note> 
               <hi>me I will honour.</hi> Who would not worke for thee <hi>O King of Nations?</hi> Who would not worke for thee <hi>O King of Saints?</hi> None ſhall loſe a word, no nor a thought for Chriſt. Wherefore (as the Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, ſo ſhall I this firſt Doctrine) <hi>My Beloved Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. laſt.</note> 
               <hi>be ye stedfaſt, unmoveable, alwayes abounding in the worke of the Lord, foraſmuch as you know that your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi> And this leades me on to the firſt part of the Gradation, obſerved and approved by Chriſt in their works, The laboriouſneſſe of them, <hi>I know thy worke, and thy labour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laborious working in a good cauſe is very pleaſing <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> unto God. <hi>God is not unrighteous to forget your worke,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 10.</note>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:64780:14"/> 
               <hi>and Labour of Love.</hi> Where we have the ſame Grada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſame words, and there, not to forget, is to delight in. God is himſelfe a pure Act, and he loves to ſee man Active: And the more active we are, the more like we are to God, and therefore the more liked of God. Likeneſſe is the ground of Love: <hi>He makes his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Angels (or meſſengers) Spirits, and his Ministers a flame of fire</hi> Spirits are the moſt active creatures living, and fire is the moſt active creature without life. Fire is the moſt operative Element, and flame is the moſt opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive part of the fire. No ſooner had man received his being, but he is put to labour (to <hi>ſerious</hi> labour, though not to <hi>conſuming</hi> labour) <hi>The Lord God tooke the man</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 15.</note> 
               <hi>which he had made, and put him into the Garden to dreſſe it, and to keep it.</hi> No ſooner was man fallen, but he was put upon <hi>ſore conſuming</hi> labour: <hi>In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 19.</note> 
               <hi>thou eat thy bread.</hi> Sinne brought in ſweat, and now not to ſweat increaſes ſinne. It is a part of our holineſſe to ſubmit to that which was a part of our curſe. The idle man is Satans Agent, and the laborious man is Gods: Not but that Satan hath nimble hands and heads in his ſervice. Satans idle man is he that will not doe the worke which God ſets him, he is ready enough to toyle (like a horſe) in the worke his owne luſt ſets him. He will not worke in the Garden of ſome honeſt imployment, or not there honeſtly; and all this while he is idle, though he ſweats and breaks his ſleep, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he doth not a ſtroake of Gods worke. Of ſuch an idle man it is chiefly ſaid, <hi>Diabolus quem occupatum non invenit ipſe occupat;</hi> He imployes whom he finds not well imployed. On the contrary, <hi>Deus quem occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum invenit ipſe occupat;</hi> God imployes them whom he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64780:14"/> finds well imployed. He found <hi>Moſes</hi> labouring on the plaines among his flockes, and ſends him to <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> for the deliverance of his people. He finds <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Andrew</hi> caſting a Net into the Sea, <hi>and he ſaith fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 4. 18, 9. Eccl. 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>me, and I will make you fiſhers of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then heare the counſell <hi>of the Preacher, Whatſoever thy hand findeth to doe, doe it with all thy might.</hi> To doe, and not with the might we have, is to doe nothing. We live no more then we worke, and we worke no more then we labour. As idleneſſe is the buriall of our ſelves, ſo unlaboriouſneſſe (if I may ſo ſpeake) is the buriall of our workes; without diligence they not onely flat, but dye upon our hands. There are ſome whoſe very buſineſſe is idleneſſe, and there are many who are idle in their buſineſſe. <hi>Seest thou a man diligent in his buſineſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 29. Rom. 12. 11.</note> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) Not ſloathfull in buſineſse</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) To be ſlow in buſineſſe is ill, but to be ſloathfull is farre worſe An induſtrious man is often wearied with working, but he is never weary of his worke. <hi>Spontaneae laſſitudines morbos loquuntur,</hi> is an Aphoriſme <note place="margin">Hip. Apb.</note> of Phyſicians. To be weary when we know not why, foreſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wes diſeaſes of the body. I am ſure it is an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of a diſeaſed ſoule. The heart of the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard is like the field of the ſluggard, <hi>overgrowne with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 24. 30</note> 
               <hi>weeds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They who worke for Chriſt, ſhould imitate Chriſt in his worke for us. <hi>I muſt worke the workes of him that ſent</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 9. 4.</note> 
               <hi>me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) There is an Emphaſis in that expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. As they ſpeake in <hi>Ieremy, Come</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 18. 18.</note> 
               <hi>let us deviſe</hi> deviſes againſt him: Which notes <hi>ſtrong plotting</hi> to miſchiefe the Prophet: ſo to <hi>worke a worke,</hi> notes the ſtrong intention of Chriſt upon it. Many doe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64780:15"/> rather <hi>play their works</hi> then worke their works: And it is obſerved, that as mean men play: ſo commonly rich and great men worke, but for recreation. Chriſt who had <hi>unſearchable riches</hi> in himſelfe, and in greatneſſe was <hi>Gods Fellow,</hi> will yet <hi>worke a worke</hi> for us. Shall we thinke any labour too great for him? Chriſt by his own labour in your cauſe (when your foules lay a bleeding) hath out-bid all the labour you have or can beſtow in his cauſe, now his Church lyes a bleeding. I know (Honourable and Beloved) you have often <hi>dined upon buſineſſe:</hi> ſo did Chriſt, <hi>My meat is to doe the will of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 4. 34.</note> 
               <hi>him that ſent me, and to finiſh his worke.</hi> I know you have laboured in the midſt of many croſſes, but Chriſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured for us <hi>upon the Croſſe.</hi> I know you have wreſtled with many difficulties; but Chriſt for your ſakes <hi>wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtled</hi> with death, that <hi>King of terrours.</hi> You have had many conflicts; but Chriſt was in an <hi>Agony, he ſweat bloud, and he ſpilt his bloud.</hi> It is ſaid of Chriſt in the <note place="margin">Iſa. 53. 11.</note> Prophet, <hi>That he ſhall ſee of the travell of his ſoule, and ſhall be ſatisfied.</hi> Whenſoever Chriſt lookes upon a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, repenting ſoule, he ſees in that the <hi>travell of his ſoule.</hi> There goes my worke (ſaith Chriſt) and this ſatisfies him. To doe good is reward enough to it ſelfe; but to ſee the good we have done, is a <hi>ſatisfying reward.</hi> Let me ſay the ſame to you, whoſe ſoules have travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and are ſtill travelling, and reſolve to travell ſtill in this great worke: When you ſhall ſee of the travell of your ſoules, you will be ſatisfied. When any one ſhall ſee a <hi>good Law,</hi> and can ſay indeed the travell of my ſoule went to the making of it. When any ſhall ſee a <hi>good Magiſtrate,</hi> and can ſay, I ſee in ſetting up him the travell of my ſoule. When any ſhall ſee a <hi>faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:64780:15"/> a ſhining Light, put into any Candleſticke, and can ſay, I ſee of the travell of my ſoule in putting of him there. When any ſhall ſee truth and peace, purity of worſhip, and piety of life fully eſtabliſhed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted in theſe Kingdomes, and can ſay indeed, I ſee in all theſe the <hi>travell of my ſoule:</hi> I will not much be troubled how to ſatisfie ſuch for their paines, I am ſure this ſight will doe it, when you ſee the <hi>travell of your</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 128. 2.</note> 
               <hi>ſoules,</hi> namely, the fruits and bleſſed effects of it, <hi>you will be ſatisfied. Bleſſed is he that feares the Lord for he ſhall eat the labour of his hands,</hi> ye and of his heart and head, and tongue. Who would feare to labour for God? who is able to make, and will make our worke our food, if we make our worke our labour. Be ye therefore as ſo many Sunnes, or rather be ye all as one Sunne, <hi>As a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 19. 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Bridegroome comming every morning out of your chambers, and rejoycing as a ſtrong man to run your race.</hi> But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, remember <hi>to runne</hi> (as Chriſt the Sunne of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 1.</note> did) <hi>with patience the race which is ſet before you.</hi> This your patterne, the Text cals for alſo; the workes of this Church were full, as of diligence, ſo of patience. I know thy labour and thy patience.</p>
            <p>It is very <hi>acceptable unto God,</hi> when we labour in his <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> worke <hi>with patience.</hi> There is a twofold patience exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed <note place="margin">He. 10. 36.</note> in our labours:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>the patience of waiting.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>the patience of ſuffering.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The patience of waiting Gods time, and the patience of ſuffering Mans reproach. They who will worke for Chriſt ſhall be exerciſed both wayes, and Chriſt is much pleaſed to ſee his holding out under both.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>the patience of waiting upon God. Ye have need of</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64780:16"/> 
               <hi>patience, that after ye have done the will of God, ye might receive the promiſe.</hi> Here is firſt doing the will of God, which includes the labour of the former point, Then comes patience. And why ſuch need of that? The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that is, the good promiſed, cannot otherwiſe be received. Why not? I ſhall touch three reaſons why?</p>
            <p>Firſt, Though God never <hi>failes his owne time,</hi> yet he ſeldome <hi>comes at ours.</hi> The Iſraelites in <hi>Egypt</hi> groaned long for deliverance; but as ſoone as the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordained by God was come, they were delivered. He did not ſtay an houre beyond that. Hence it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that the Lord ſmote the firſt borne of <hi>Egypt</hi> at <note place="margin">Gen. 15. 13. Exod. 12. 40. 41.</note> midnight, and why at midnight? becauſe then exactly the 400. or 430. yeares of their captivity were expired, and they determining at midnight, God came preſently, he deferred them not till Morning for their deliverance. <hi>It came to paſſe, ſaith</hi> Moſes, <hi>at the end of the</hi> 430 <hi>yeares, even the ſelf-ſame day it came to paſſe, that all the Hoaſts of the Lord came out from the Land of</hi> Egypt. So <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> was ſlaine in the night, <hi>In that night,</hi> &amp;c. And why in that night? becauſe then exactly the 70. yeares of the <note place="margin">Dan. 5. 30.</note> Jewes captivity in <hi>Babylon</hi> were ended; And they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at night, God ſtayed not till the Morning. We have a ſaying much like our ſelves, <hi>a day breaks no ſquare,</hi> but it is not ſo with God. We read once of <hi>the ſhortning of the dayes of evill,</hi> but never of the <hi>lengthening of them.</hi> Thus God never failes his owne time. And it is as true, that he ſeldome comes at ours. The Summer is ended, and we are not ſaved, ſay they in <hi>Ieremy,</hi> they look'd for ſalvation that Summer at furtheſt. We are <hi>ſhort-breathed,</hi> and <hi>ſhort-ſighted,</hi> and ſo, very apt to <hi>ante-date</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes <note place="margin">Ier. 8. 20.</note>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:64780:16"/> in regard of their accompliſhment: That which is but a moment in the <hi>Kalendar of Heaven,</hi> ſeemes <hi>an age</hi> to us. This and the remedy are put together in the ſecond of <hi>Habbakuk,</hi> where the viſion is ſaid <hi>to tarry,</hi> and <note place="margin">Hab. 2: 2.</note> not to <hi>tarry.</hi> It <hi>tarries not</hi> in reference to the <hi>time fixed</hi> by Chriſt, but it <hi>tarries</hi> in reference to the time <hi>ſuppoſed by us.</hi> What muſt we doe in this caſe? if it tarry, wait for it, there is no <hi>remedy but patience.</hi> Lengthen pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and that will make the time ſhort.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the preſent dealings of God with a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, doe many times carry a ſhew of contrariety againſt his owne promiſes and purpoſes. He brings <hi>Iſrael</hi> to <note place="margin">Ex. 14.</note> the Sea, and ſuffers an Army to incamp at their backs, when he meant to deliver them. <hi>Clouds and darkneſse are</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 97. 2.</note> 
               <hi>round about him, when judgement and juſtice are the habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Throne.</hi> Without patience there is no abiding under theſe clouds and darkneſſe, till the light of his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and judgement breaketh forth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God cannot beare it with patience, that we ſhould <hi>limit him,</hi> either to the time, or manner, or meanes of help. He complaines of the Jewes for this preſumption, <hi>they limited the holy One of Iſrael.</hi> It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable to circumſcribe an infinite wiſedome and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. <note place="margin">Pſ. 78. 41.</note> He will worke, but when he pleaſes, and how he pleaſes, and by what inſtruments he pleaſes, and if he pleaſe without inſtruments, and if he pleaſe, by weake and improbable, by deſpiſed and exploded in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments. Except patience, there is nothing can keep us cloſe to the worke of God, while himſelfe takes, and of right may take ſuch tranſcendent liberty.</p>
            <p>As thus in labouring for God we ſhall be put to pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in waiting his time: So,</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:64780:17"/>
            <p>Secondly, there will be uſe of patience to ſuffer the miſ-apprehenſions, wrongs, reproaches, and oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men. Firſt, the miſapprehenſions of thoſe for whom you labour. Some are for a while more ſicke of their phyſicke, then they were of the diſeaſe, and then the Phyſitian muſt have the patience to heare from his Patient, <hi>you will kill me.</hi> When <hi>Moſes</hi> was labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to deliver the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from their hard bondage, reade their opinion of him. <hi>The people met</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod 5. 20, 21.</note> Aaron, <hi>who ſtood in the way as they came forth from</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh, <hi>and they ſayd unto them, The Lord looke upon you, and iudge, becauſe ye have made our ſavour to be abhorred in the eyes of</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>and in the eyes of his ſervants, to put a ſword into their hands to ſlay us.</hi> They thought he would undoe them quite, and while he attempted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their liberty would endanger their lives. Againe, they expoſtulate with him at the Red Sea: <hi>They ſaid</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14. 11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>becauſe there were no graves in</hi> Egypt, <hi>haſt thou taken us away to dye in the wilderneſſe? wherefore haſt thou dealt thus with us, to carry us out of</hi> Egypt? <hi>Is not this the word that we did tell thee in</hi> Egypt, <hi>ſaying, Let us alone that we may ſerve the Egyptians? For it had been better for us that we ſhould ſerve the</hi> Egyptians, <hi>then that we ſhould dye in the Wilderneſſe.</hi> How angry were this people with their begun deliverance? how did they preferre bondage before it, and put this miracle of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy among, yea below their greateſt afflictions? What patience almoſt could beare this? but who could beare it without patience?</p>
            <p>Further in the ſecond place, they who worke for Chriſt ſhall be ſure to meet with reproaches, ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and oppoſitions from profeſſed enemies. When
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64780:17"/> 
               <hi>Nehemiah</hi> labours to reſtore <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> he is ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">Neh. 2. 19.</note> with rebellion. <hi>What will you rebell againſt the King,</hi> cry <hi>Sanballat</hi> and <hi>Tobiah</hi> and <hi>Geſhem</hi> the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bian.</hi> In a ſence we may ſay of this reproach, as <hi>Hierome of hereſie, it is ſuch as doth not become a man to be patient under it.</hi> None ought to be ſo patient under it, as not to vindicate his loyalty, yet every one ought to be ſo patient under it, as not for feare of ſuch aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to forſake his duty. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> confutes the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, not by deſiſting from his worke, but by the faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and integrity of his worke. By that time pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath digeſted this or the like reproaches, you muſt looke for ſcoffs. So in the ſame place, <hi>They laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us to ſcorne</hi> (ſaith good <hi>Nehemiah) and derided us.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Neh. 4. 2, 3.</note> In the fourth Chapter they are jeering againe. <hi>What do theſe feeble Iewes? Will they fortifie themſelves? will they ſacrifice? will they make an end in a day? Will they revive the ſtones out of the heapes of rubbiſh that are burnt? Even that which they build if a Fox goe up, he will even breake down their ſtone-wall.</hi> Words as full of ſcorne, as prophane wit or rancoured malice could make them. And the weight of theſe ſcoffs, did lie ſo heavy upon the ſpirit of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> that he could not eaſe himſelfe, but by breathing Heaven ward. <hi>Heare</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Neh 4. 4.</note> 
               <hi>ô our God, for we are deſpiſed. Woe be unto thoſe who by ſcoffing ſet</hi> Nehemiah's <hi>a praying Scoffs were never any match for prayers, nor ever will be.</hi> There is no greater argument of a deſperate cauſe, nor clearer prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtick of ruine to ſuch, then when they begin to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride. For though the patience of men may and ought to beare even this: yet the patience of God will not. When ſcoffers whet their tongues, then aſſuredly God
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64780:18"/> is whetting his Sword. Once more you have need of patience; for when you have borne reproach and deti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion daily, then looke for contrary plottings and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. The Hiſtories of <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> are ſo full of theſe, that I referre you to the whole. What, raiſing of Parties, What hiring of Councellors, What Letters to the Court, What bribing of <hi>Nehemiah's</hi> near friends to take them off, could doe, was done, in oppoſition of his deſigne. And while God hath ſuch a worke to doe, and men have ſuch corruptions in their hearts, and the Devill ſuch temptations in his hand, the like will be done againe And if ſo, <hi>O Patience, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence!</hi> who can doe any thing for Chriſt without thee?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore let patience have a perfect worke,</hi> otherwiſe <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> you can never bring your <hi>workes to perfection. In patience</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iam 1. 3. Luk. 21. 19</note> 
               <hi>poſſeſſe your ſoules.</hi> As faith gives us the poſſeſſion of Chriſt, ſo patience gives us the poſſeſſion of our ſelves. An impatient perſon is out of his owne power, his parts and abilities are as loſt to him, he cannot uſe them. Neither is there any nearer way to our owne ends and comforts, then patience. Firſt wait patiently on God: <hi>For the Lord is a God of Iudgement, bleſsed are all they that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 36. 18.</note> 
               <hi>wait for him.</hi> You will ſay, there <hi>might be bleſſedneſſe</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in vvaiting upon a <hi>God of mercy.</hi> But hovv can vve be bleſſed in vvaiting upon a <hi>God of Iudgement?</hi> Is there any Motive in Judgement to invite attendance?</p>
            <p>I anſvver: Firſt, <hi>Iudgement</hi> is not here taken as oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to <hi>Mercy,</hi> but as oppoſed to <hi>ſeverity and rigour. O Lord correct me, but with iudgement, not in thine anger, leſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 10. 24. Ier. 30. 11.</note> 
               <hi>thou bring me to nothing.</hi> To correct in judgement and in meaſure are the ſame,; <hi>Iudgement is the moderation</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64780:18"/> 
               <hi>of anger.</hi> It is a bleſſed thing to wait on him, who we are ſure, makes reaſon, not rage, the rule of his Actions, who holds every paſſion in the <hi>Golden Bridle of Moderation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly judgement is here taken for <hi>equity,</hi> as it is oppoſite <hi>to injuſtice,</hi> either in not puniſhing the wicked, or in not relieving the good. That man is bleſſed who waits upon a juſt Judge with a juſt cauſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, judgement is here taken for <hi>wiſedome,</hi> as Iudgement is oppoſed <hi>to folly and weakneſſe of underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi> It is a great burthen to wait upon a foole; but we can eaſily ſtay for the reſolutions of the wiſe: who we are ſure, have the compaſſe of a buſineſſe in their heads, and are skilled in timing and ordering every circumſtance. How bleſſed then are they, who while they worke for, can wait upon this God of judgement: whoſe moderation, and juſtice, and wiſedome are ſuch, as will not ſuffer him either to doe any thing before the ſet, the fit time come, nor to ſtay the doing of it one minute after. Hence the Church is brought in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring God, and rejoycing that ſhee had waited on him. None ever repented of this patience. <hi>Loe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 25. 9.</note> 
               <hi>this is our God, we have waited for him, and he will ſave us. This is the Lord, we have waited for him, we will be glad and rejoyce in his ſalvation.</hi> The words have a ſound of victory and triumph in them. It ſhould ſeem the enemies had mockt them (as they did <hi>David)</hi> with their God; <hi>Where is now your God?</hi> They had (it is <note place="margin">Pſ. 42 10.</note> like) blaſphemouſly ſcorned them, concerning the true God (as <hi>Elijah</hi> did <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts juſtly, concerning that I doll, when it delayed to help them) <hi>either he is talking, or he is purſuing, or he is in a iourney, or peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 King. 18. 27.</note> 
               <hi>he ſleepeth, and muſt be awaked.</hi> At the noiſe of this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64780:19"/> blaſphemy, <hi>the Lord awaked as one out of ſleep, and like</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78. 65, 66.</note> 
               <hi>a mighty man that ſhouteth by reaſon of wine, and he ſmote his enemies in their hinder parts</hi> (they fled) <hi>he put them to perpetuall ſhame.</hi> Then his people with an <hi>Ecce</hi> of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration <hi>cry him up, Loe, this is our God, we have waited for him.</hi> They who but a ſeaſon wait for God, ſhall have matter of glorying in him for ever.</p>
            <p>Secondly, beare (I beſeech you) with patience the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of men: For reproach is a great proof of ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Work on, though men ſcoffe on.</hi> And hereby you ſhall (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of himſelf and his Fellow-labourers <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 4, 8.</note> in the Goſpell) <hi>approve your ſelves as the Miniſters of God (in this your worke for the Church and Common-wealth) in much patience, in afflictions, in neceſſities, in diſtreſſes: by honour and diſhonour, by evill report and good report, as deceivers and yet true.</hi> It hath been ſaid, that to doe well, and heare ill, is Kingly; I am ſure it is Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anly. Chriſt never did more, or better for us, then when he was moſt derided. Here was the patience of Chriſt, here the ſtrength and victory of his Love. It had ſhewed the mighty love of Chriſt, in the worke of our redemption; if, when he came into the world, the world had entertained him with honour, and had put him to death onely (as <hi>Caiaphas</hi> gave counſell) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>it was expedient that one ſhould dye for the people;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 18. 14</note> but to come and dye for thoſe, who (he knew before) would mocke and revile him; yea, to doe the worke while they actually reviled him: <hi>This was ſtupendious love and patience to a miracle. It is commendable to do good,</hi> while all praiſe, commend, approve, and honour; but to doe good while multitudes of all ſorts and ſizes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, revile, ſcoffe and ſlander, is admirable, is <hi>quid</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:64780:19"/> 
               <hi>divinum, and bids up faire, to the love of a Saviour.</hi> No man ever undertook a great work but he was miſ-underſtood: <hi>Wilt thou kill me, ſaith that Iew to Moſes,</hi> when he came onely <hi>to pacifie him,</hi> and <hi>ſave them all.</hi> If your worke <note place="margin">Act. 7. 25.</note> be miſscalled, or miſ-reported by men, patience will make this a <hi>vantage ground,</hi> for the raiſing of your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation with God. What the Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticke ſervants,</hi> is as true of the <hi>Publicke ſervants</hi> of a State: <hi>If when ye doe well and ſuffer for it (the tongue is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 20.</note> 
               <hi>a perſecutor,</hi> Gal. 4. 29.) <hi>ye take it patiently, tbis is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table with God:</hi> Or as the Greeke more elegantly, <hi>this</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>is thanks with God,</hi> that is, certainly for this God will thanke you.</p>
            <p>But ſuch, who can endure moſt reproach, can leaſt of all endure impiety. He who is a <hi>very Atlas</hi> in bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>a world of ſhame,</hi> cannot with any liking <hi>beare a grain of ſinne.</hi> And when ſinne growes great he hath no pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to beare it. Such was the holy and zealous tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of theſe <hi>Epheſians,</hi> though they had unconquered patience for <hi>waiting and ſuffering,</hi> yet they had none for <hi>ſinning. Thou canſt not beare them that are evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the firſt ſort or kind of their works here ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, and by Chriſt approved, the removing or taking away of the evill. Hence obſerve, That,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is (as an Argument ſo) the duty of thoſe who are</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>good, not to beare them that are evill.</hi> It is an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for from hence this Church receives Letters Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimoniall from Heaven of their goodneſſe. The height and elevation of grace, may well be taken by our oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition againſt evill. The more holy any man is, the leſſe can he beare with his owne ſinne: For this, I conceive to be an experimentall truth, That the leſſe corruption
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64780:20"/> any one hath remaining in him, the greater burden it is unto him: And they who have moſt corruption in them feele it leaſt. Now as it is in reference to the evill in our ſelves, ſo proportionably to that in others. The more holy any man is, the leſſe he can beare with thoſe who are unholy and prophane.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall proſecute the point onely under the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a duty. It is the duty of thoſe who are good, not to beare ſuch as are evill.</p>
            <p>Evill men, and evill manners are heavy burdens. They are <hi>burdens to God: I am preſſed under you</hi> (ſaith <note place="margin">Am. 2. 13. Iſa. 1. 24.</note> God to ſuch) <hi>as a Cart is preſſed with ſheaves.</hi> God will not beare them. <hi>I will eaſe me of mine adverſaries.</hi> They are burdens to whole <hi>Kingdomes</hi> and <hi>Churches;</hi> they cannot beare them; they ſinke and ruine under them, <hi>if not removed.</hi> They are burdens to all good men; they muſt not beare them, it is their duty to remoove them.</p>
            <p>For the clearing of this point, I ſhall open thoſe two principall termes in it:</p>
            <p>Firſt, who theſe evill ones are that muſt not be borne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what it imports, Not to beare them.</p>
            <p>To the former. In a ſence, all men living on the face of the earth are evill men. <hi>Why calleſt thou me good,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>to one who knew no more of him then Man: There is none good but God,</hi> ſcil. <hi>eſſentially, perfectly, and indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 19. 17.</note> There is none that is good and ſinneth not; there is none that doth good, and ſinneth not. Now though every evill man be a burden; yet there is a neceſſity of bearing many, and a duty of bearing ſome. <hi>We that are ſtrong</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) ought to beare the infirmities</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 151.</note>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:64780:20"/> 
               <hi>of the weake.</hi> Infirmity is a degree of evill: And theſe weake ones troubled themſelves about things they nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not, about the things they had no juſt cauſe to be troubled at (for to be troubled at any thing which gives a juſt cauſe of offence, is not weakneſſe but ſtrength) yet <hi>they muſt be borne with.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt therefore diſtinguiſh of evill men.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſome are private and cloſe offenders, others are publicke and ſcandalous.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſome are weake and ſcrupulous, others are obſtinate and pertinacious.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſome are evill-doers, and evill-practiſers onely, others are evill-promoters and evill-plotters.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſome are ſeduced and miſled, others are ſeducers and leaders into miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, ſome are curable and willing to be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, others are incurable and hate to be reformed.</p>
            <p>Such as are publicke and ſcandalous, ſuch as are obſtinate and pertinacious, ſuch as are evill-plotters and evill-promoters, ſuch as are ſeducers and miſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſuch as are incurable and hate to be reformed; theſe, and if there be any like unto them; ought not to be borne.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe who are cloſe and private offenders, they come not under any legall Cognizance, and though many offences of ſuch may be inſufferable in their owne nature, yet there is a neceſſity of bearing them: For ſuch as are weake and ſcrupulous, it was (a little before) proved a duty to beare them: For thoſe who are onely evill-doers, and ſeduced, they being willing to reforme and be cured, in ſome caſes (I ſay in ſome caſes) <hi>Iuſtice may beare them, and charity in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:64780:21"/>
            <p>For as it was in the Lawes of Leproſie among the Jewes: Many who had riſings and ſcabs, or ſpots in <note place="margin">Lev 13.</note> the skin of the fleſh, were not yet to be judged unclean, and put <hi>out of the Camp.</hi> There were certaine <hi>Criteria,</hi> ſignes or tokens given by God himſelfe, on which the Prieſt was to ground his judgement. So now many have ſinnes and errours (whereof thoſe ſpots and riſings were a figure) who yet muſt not be thruſt away from us preſently. Such indeed muſt, whoſe ſpirituall ſores carry a proportion (if we can find it out) with thoſe corporall. It is agreed on by all, that thoſe leprous ſpots did note out our ſeverall malignities of ſoule-diſeaſes; but what degrees or kinds of ſoul-diſeaſes is not agreed. It were to be <hi>too much an Origeniſt,</hi> ſtrictly to enquire about all, or confidently to conclude about any; yet there can be no danger in offering a conjecture ſuting the rules before given.</p>
            <p>I ſhall inſtance onely in foure of thoſe ſignes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the firſt, which is alſo often mentioned in that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is, <hi>when the haire in the ſoare is turned white, and when the plague in ſight is deeper then the skin.</hi> The white <note place="margin">Lev. 13. 3.</note> haire may note ſuch as have continued long, and are growne old in any wickedneſſe. The deepneſſe of the plague, ſuch whoſe wickedneſſe is not onely acted by their hands, but ſeated in their hearts, and ſunke into their ſpirits. A reſolved, ſtudied way of evill, is a <hi>deepe ſoare; deeper then</hi> the skin, <hi>ſuch men are far worſe then they appeare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond token of Leproſie, was, <hi>when the skab did ſpread much in the skin.</hi> Though it had no white haires, <note place="margin">V. 4, 8.</note> though it were no deeper then the skin, yet if it did ſpread much in the skin, ſuch an one was a Leper. It
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64780:21"/> may figure ſuch, whoſe ſinnefull courſes (after admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) are <hi>gaining and growing</hi> ſtill upon themſelves, or are ſcattered and ſpread to the infecting of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>A third token was, <hi>The quick, raw (or living) fleſh in the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">V 10, 11, 14.</note> 
               <hi>riſing.</hi> It is one of the moſt remarkeable things in all this law, that <hi>quick or ſound fleſh</hi> in the ſoare ſhould be judged Leproſie, and the man uncleane: Whereas, if the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie <hi>covered all his fleſh,</hi> he was pronounced cleane. <note place="margin">V. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Hereby firſt may be meant, ſuch as juſtifie themſelves and their wickedneſſe, as <hi>Ionah</hi> ſaid of his paſſion, <hi>I</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ion 44.</note> 
               <hi>doe well to be angry, angry even unto death:</hi> ſo they of their unwarrantable, yea abominable wayes, both in practiſe and worſhip, <hi>We doe well to doe ſo, even to the death; this is living fleſh in the midſt of the ſoare.</hi> When a ſinne ſhall be maintained for holineſſe, and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſtood to for pure devotion: Whereas, he who humbleth and judgeth himſelfe, is like him, who had the Leproſie all over, and might be declared cleane.</p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, ſuch may poſſibly be figured by the quicke raw fleſh, who ſinne againſt the <hi>light of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> and the <hi>quickneſse,</hi> yea <hi>rawneſse of a galled Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A fourth note of Leproſie was, <hi>When after the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a bile in the skin, in the place of it a ſoare did ariſe,</hi> with the former Symptomes of <hi>white haire, and deepneſſe in the fleſh.</hi> This may ſignifie relapſers, whoſe ſinne-ſoares <note place="margin">V. 18, 19, 20.</note> breake out after promiſes and appearances of healing: Such as <hi>returne with the dog to their vomit, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 22.</note> 
               <hi>with the Sow that is waſhed to their wallowing in the mire.</hi> Many Relapſers prove as bad as Revolters, who of all men <hi>are moſt profound to make ſlaughter,</hi> and doe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe; <note place="margin">Hoſ. 5. 2.</note>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:64780:22"/> Therefore beware of them, theſe are not to be borne. From theſe and the ſubſequent ſignes of Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, laid downe in this Chapter, with the former diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, we may diſcover who thoſe evill men are that muſt not be borne.</p>
            <p>The ſecond enquiry is, what, <hi>not bearing doth import.</hi> As all the <hi>Negative Commandements</hi> have in them an <hi>Affirmative:</hi> ſo hath this Negative rule in the Text. Not to beare, denyes and affirmes.</p>
            <p>In the Negative ſence, <hi>Not to beare,</hi> is, firſt, not to like or conſent unto.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Not to countenance or uphold.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Not to allow or permit, which is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called a Toleration.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Not to hide or conceale.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Not to pitty or compaſſionate.</p>
            <p>In the Affirmative ſence, Not to beare, is, firſt to admoniſh and reprove.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To oppoſe and reſiſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To cenſure and puniſh.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, To remove and caſt out.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, In ſome caſes to deſtroy and cut off, either firſt, by the <hi>ſword of the Law,</hi> or ſecondly, <hi>by the Law of the ſword,</hi> either in a Iudiciall way, or in a Martiall way.</p>
            <p>In the thirteenth of <hi>Deutronomy,</hi> we have both ſences expreſſed, in the caſe of Entiſers to Idolatry. <hi>If thy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 13. 6</note> 
               <hi>brother, the ſonne of thy mother, or thy ſonne or thy daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or the wife of thy boſome, or thy friend which is as thine owne ſoule, entiſe thee ſecretly, ſaying, Let us goe and ſerve other gods, which thou haſt not knowne, thou, nor thy fathers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou ſhalt not conſent unto him, nor hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 8.</note>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:64780:22"/> 
               <hi>unto him, neither ſhall thine eye pitty him, neither ſhalt thou ſpare, neither ſhalt thou conceale him.</hi> Here are the Negative Acts of Not bearing. The higheſt of the Affirmative followes in the next words, <hi>But thou ſhalt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 9.</note> 
               <hi>ſurely kil him.</hi> Not privately or without Iudgment, <hi>That, were to commit murder in puniſhing of Idolatry. Thou ſhalt ſurely kill him,</hi> notes the <hi>Order</hi> of killing ſuch, after <hi>publicke-Iudgement,</hi> not the killing of them without <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Iudgement.</hi> As it is expounded in the next words, <hi>Thine hand ſhall be firſt upon him to put him to death, and afterwards the hand of all the people.</hi> So was the Low of ſtoning to death; <hi>The hands of the witneſſes ſhall be firſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 17. 7</note> 
               <hi>upon him.</hi> And ſo much legality was obſerved in the ſtoning of <hi>Stephen,</hi> the <hi>Witneſſes began.</hi> But to the point, <note place="margin">Act. 7. 58. Pſ. 101. 8.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> reſolves as high: <hi>I will early deſtroy all the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of the Land, that I may cut off all wicked doers from the City of the Lord.</hi> His ſonne <hi>Solomon</hi> directs as high: <hi>Take away the droſſe from the ſilver, and there ſhall come forth a veſsell for the finer. Take away the wicked from the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 25. 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>King, and his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed in righteouſneſſe.</hi> Wicked men are droſſe, they have no good mettall in them; they can never be made fit <hi>veſſels to ſerve,</hi> or <hi>currant money to enrich, or jewels to adorne the Throne:</hi> For the taking this <hi>droſse away,</hi> he doth not arme a <hi>hand of violence,</hi> but a <hi>hand of juſtice. The very droſſe about a Princes Throne muſt be removed with duty and reſpect.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> reproves the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> for holding communion with an <hi>inceſtuous perſon;</hi> and charges them <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.</note> to puniſh him (as high as the power of a Church can reach) with Excommunication; <hi>Therefore put away from among your ſelves that wicked perſon.</hi> Himſelf could <note place="margin">Ver. 13.</note> not beare falſe brethren (they are worſe then open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64780:23"/> for an houre. <hi>To whom we gave place by ſubjection,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>no not for an houre.</hi> His imprecation (in the ſame Epiſtle) goes deeper then his practiſe. <hi>I would they were even cut</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 12.</note> 
               <hi>off which trouble you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, Firſt, ſuch evill men will not long be <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> evill alone. Evill men endanger the good; As weeds the corne, or bad humours the bloud, or an infected houſe the neighbourhood. <hi>Nemo errat ſibi ipſi, ſed demen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ſpargit in proximos.</hi> The Apoſtle compares them <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sen Ep.</hi> 94</note> to <hi>Leven,</hi> which quickly ſowreth the <hi>whole Lump.</hi> On this ground he adviſeth <hi>Timothy to ſhun prophane and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>vaine bablings</hi> (that is prophane and vaine bablers) <hi>for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2 16, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.</note> 
               <hi>they will increaſe unto more ungodlineſſe, and their word will eat as doth a Canker or a Gangrene.</hi> This is often gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as a reaſon why the Iewes might not beare the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites. <hi>Thou ſhalt make no Covenant with them nor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 23. 32. 33.</note> 
               <hi>with their gods, they ſhall not dwell in thy Land, leſt they make thee ſinne againſt me.</hi> And when contrary to this rule they did beare them, the event is anſwerable to that minatory praediction. <hi>They did not deſtroy the Nations concerning whom the Lord commanded them; but were min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 106. 34, 35, 36.</note> 
               <hi>with the heathen</hi> (then immediately followes) <hi>and learned their works</hi> He means not works of Art or Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culture, of war or peace; but of falſe worſhip and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry) <hi>They ſerved their Idols, which were a ſnare unto them.</hi> It was an ancient hereſie of the Pelagians (denying the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug Tom.</hi> 7. <hi>lib <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de pec mer, c.</hi> 9.</note> propagation of ſin) that all ſinne is handed from one to another by example, and taken in by imitation. But it is a too much experienced truth, that ſinne is mightily increaſed and ſpread by example and imitation. We have ſeen dangerous, if not deſtructive errours, and vain ſuperſtitions ſpreading farre and neare, when counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64780:23"/> with the practiſe, and by the tenets of ſome in great place. Thoſe opinions and innovations which at firſt were begun by a few, and hiſt at by many, grew ſuddenly into credit with moſt, and would in time have invaded all.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if we beare ſuch, though we could <hi>eſcape</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>the pollution,</hi> yet we ſhall fall under <hi>the guilt of their ſins.</hi> We ſinne in others, while we ſuffer them to ſinne: We commit all the evill which is in our power to hinder, if we hinder it not. <hi>Vitia aliorum ſi feras, facis tua.</hi> We become guilty of other mens ſinnes, not onely by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, counſelling, and approving them; but (if wee may) by not ſtopping and reſtraining them. <hi>I will judge the houſe of</hi> Eli <hi>for ever (ſaith the Lord) for the iniquity which he knoweth, becauſe his ſons made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>vile, and he reſtrained them not.</hi> He gave them fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly advice, but he did not uſe his Fatherly Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. When Chriſt cals his people out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> this <note place="margin">Rev. 18. 4.</note> is added as a reaſon, <hi>that ye be not partakers of her ſinnes:</hi> Which partaking in her ſinne, as it notes danger of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, of getting ſome taint and ſpots in <hi>Babylon:</hi> ſo it notes alſo danger of contracting ſome guilt, by not oppoſing or proteſting againſt the Idolatry there pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, and hereſie there maintained, though they keepe themſelves pure from all practiſe of the one, or mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the other. And that,</p>
            <p>Thirdly (which is an inevitable conſequent of the two <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> former) if we either way-beare their ſinne, we ſhall likewiſe beare their puniſhment. This is joyned as a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon of their comming out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> in the place before cited, <hi>that ye receive not of her plagues.</hi> And <note place="margin">Rev. 18. 4.</note> when the people of God have ſtrength and power, they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64780:24"/> are as much obliged to caſt <hi>Babylon</hi> out from amongſt them, <hi>leaſt they be partakers of her plagues: For God will plague</hi> Babylon <hi>whereſoever he finds her.</hi> There is no ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in being near them who are under the curſe of God. <hi>Eſcape for thy life</hi> (ſay the Angels to <hi>Lot) looke not behind</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19. 17.</note> 
               <hi>thee, neither ſtay thou in all the plaine: Eſcape to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, left thou be conſumed. Depart, I pray you, from the tents of theſe wicked men</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation) <note place="margin">Num. 16. 26.</note> 
               <hi>and touch nothing of theirs, left ye be conſumed in all their ſinnes.</hi> And if there be ſo much danger in <hi>being neare them, what danger is there in bearing them. A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of fooles ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> When an overflowing <note place="margin">Pro. 13. 20.</note> ſtorme ſweeps away the wicked, the taile of it may daſh their beſt neighbours.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when God doth not puniſh them with the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> wicked, he uſually puniſhes them by the wicked. If they are not ſcourged with them, theſe become their ſcourges: Eſpecially, when for feare of trouble we beare them, God (to confute our policies) makes them both our burden and our trouble. <hi>Take heed unto your ſelves</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> to <hi>Iſrael) that ye love the Lord your God: Elſe, if ye doe in any wiſe goe backe, and cleave to the remnant of thoſe Nations, even thoſe that remaine among</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioſh 23. 11, 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>you, and ſhall make marriages with them, and goe in unto them, and they to you: Know for a certainty, that the Lord your God will no more drive out any of theſe Nations from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you; but they ſhall be ſnares and traps unto you, and ſcourges in your ſides, and thornes in your eyes, untill you periſh from off this good Land, which the Lord your God hath given you.</hi> A Text, whoſe Comment (in a great part) hath lately been made in <hi>Ireland;</hi> and is written to us in the <hi>bloud of many thouſands.</hi> Of all the evill
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64780:24"/> which hath fallen upon them we may ſay, <hi>this is your bearing with evill.</hi> You have borne them, and they have broken you. It is better to learne by other calamities then our owne. And to take <hi>Example,</hi> then be made <hi>One.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Not to beare the evill is mercy, not onely to <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>5</label> the good, but to the evill. You cannot be more cruell to them, then in ſparing them. The greateſt ſtroake that ever <hi>Iſrael</hi> felt from the hand of God was this, <hi>Why</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould they be ſtricken any more. Ephraims</hi> ſoreſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Idolatry was this, <hi>Let him alone.</hi> If you would <note place="margin">Hoſ. 5. 17.</note> be a friend to evill men, wound them. A kiſſe is enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Favour and complyance fattens their ſinnes, and hardens their hearts, whereas reproofe and puniſhment may poſſibly reforme and heale them. It was the wiſh of that good King; <hi>Let the righteous ſmite me, it ſhall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 141. 5.</note> 
               <hi>be a kindneſſe; and let him reprove me, it ſhall be an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Oyle, which ſhall not breake my head.</hi> There is no ſtanding ſtill in evill, the beſt, if let alone, when they doe amiſſe, will be worſe; How bad then will the worſt be if they be let alone. And when they are at the worſt, it is worſt for themſelves. Is it not then a kindneſſe to ſmite them? It is alwayes a <hi>kindneſse offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> though often it be not a <hi>kindneſse received:</hi> For of many that of <hi>Solomon</hi> is verified, <hi>Though thou ſhouldst</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27. 22</note> 
               <hi>bray a foole in a morter among wheate with a pestell; yet will not his fooliſhneſſe depart from him.</hi> And the Apoſtle is expreſſe in a Propheticke threat, <hi>Evill men and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 13.</note> (that is, evill men who are ſeducers, or among all evill men, eſpecially ſeducers) <hi>ſhall waxe worſe and worſe, deceiving and being deceived.</hi> They couzen others, and the Devill couzens them. But if theſe will not receive
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64780:25"/> this kindneſſe of ſmiting <hi>(ad correctionem)</hi> to amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it will be a kindneſſe, which they cannot put off, to ſmite them (if they by Law deſerve it) <hi>ad ruinam,</hi> to death. Seeing they as through the patience of God, ſo through the patience of man in bearing and forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them, doe but <hi>treaſure up wrath againſt the day of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 5.</note> 
               <hi>wrath, and the Revelation of the righteous judgement of God.</hi> The judgement of many had been (comparative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) Light, if they had not been ſo much borne with. As favour to a murderer often kils a ſecond man, ſo it often addes a degree of wrath to the ſecond death of the murderer. And this is proportionably true of every evill one we beare, unleſſe ſuch repent, they poore ſoules beare the more for ever.</p>
            <p>The point yet is lyable to ſome Objections from <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> Scripture, I ſhall anſwer two Texts which may alſo be <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 6</note> a clearing to others.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Love beareth all things.</hi> If all things, then evill things, for many things are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Love is indeed the badge of Chriſts Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>1</label> the very <hi>Genius</hi> of the Saints. And love hath broad ſhoulders, it can beare much, yea <hi>love can beare all things,</hi> which conſiſt with love; but ſin doth not. Love is the fullfilling of the Law, and ſin is the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the Law, therefore love cannot beare ſinne. <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Beare one anothers burdens</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Galatians) and ſo fulfill the Law of Chriſt.</hi> Love can beare any thing that concernes the fulfilling of the Law, but if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nything be a breaking of the Law it cannot beare that. <hi>It can beare</hi> the infirmities and paſſions of others, <hi>It can beare</hi> the afflictions and ſufferings of others, <hi>it can beare</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:64780:25"/> the wrongs and injuries of others againſt it ſelfe, but <hi>it cannot beare wrongs and injuries done to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Charity is not contrary to Juſtice. Wee <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>2</label> may love the perſon while we reprove, oppoſe or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the offender. God himſelfe puniſheth where hee loves. <hi>Thou waſt a God who forgaveſt them, though thou</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 99. 8.</note> 
               <hi>tookeſt vengeance of their inventions.</hi> And man may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, where he taketh vengeance. It is ſaid, <hi>that God ſuffered (or bore) the manners of the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>fourty yeares in the wilderneſſe.</hi> He bare them indeed in the way of much patience, but he did not beare them in a way of the leaſt complyance. <hi>For with many of them God was not well pleaſed,</hi> that is, he was exceedingly <note place="margin">Act. 13. 18. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Cor. 10. 5</note> diſpleaſed (there is a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the Apoſtles expreſſion, (as the words following doe evince) <hi>For they were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne</hi> (or as another place hath it, their carkaſſe fell) <hi>in the wilderneſſe.</hi> Theirs was a great puniſhment, and therefore Gods was a great diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Chriſt is all Love as well as all lovely. He is but</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Love Incarnate.</hi> And his Love is made the patterne of ours. <hi>Walke in Love as Chriſt hath loved us.</hi> Now Ieſus Chriſt though he came into the world with love enough, to beare the ſins of every man in the world, and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to beare the ſins of all the Elect: ſo as to ſuffer and dye for them; yet he would not beare ſo much as one ſinne of any one man, ſo as to countenance or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with it. He would not beare Scribes and Phariſees, hypocrites, as full of love as he was. He would not beare buyers and ſellers in the Temple, as full of Love as he was, but whipt them out. He would not beare his owne <hi>Peter</hi> when he ſpake fooliſhly, as full of Love as he was, but rebukes him with, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:64780:26"/> Mat. 16. 23. Chriſt in love bore all our ſinnes, but he will not beare with any. Doe not out-love your rule, and then beare as much evill as you can.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the love of our ſelves is the meaſure of our <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>4</label> love to others; <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 19. 19</note> Now no man ought ſo to love himſelfe, as to beare his owne ſinne-evils. Holy ſelf-love caſts the firſt ſtone at a mans owne ſinne. Therefore it cannot be love to others to beare them in evill. No, the Spirit of God doth interpret that as hatred. <hi>Thou ſhalt not hate thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lev. 19. 17</note> 
               <hi>in thy heart: Thou ſhalt in any wiſe rebuke thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and not ſuffer ſinne upon him.</hi> Or (as it is rendred out of the Originall) <hi>that thou beare not ſinne for him.</hi> To oppoſe evill in thy brother is the beſt way to doe him good, and thy ſelfe too.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it may be objected, That the Maſter of <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> the field not onely forbids his ſervants to plucke up the Tares, but adds, <hi>Let both grow together untill the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer firſt, by that approved Maxime <hi>(Scriptura</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Parabolica non eſt Argumentativa)</hi> We may not argue from every particular in a Parable, but onely from the <hi>Generall Scope of it.</hi> The Scope of the Parable is onely this, to ſhew, that good and bad will be mixt together to the end of the world. Or it ſhewes what God (out of his Prerogative) will ſuffer: Not what man (in duty) ought. It holds forth the pleaſure of God to us, to which we muſt ſubmit: Not a patterne, or a rule by which we muſt walke. God is able if he pleaſe, to plucke up at once all the tares and weeds in the world, yet he lets them grow: But this is no warrant for us to let them grow, which are in our lawfull power to pluck up.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:64780:26"/>
            <p>Againe, the letter of the Parable is cleare, that he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>2</label> onely ſuch a plucking up of Tares, as by which <note place="margin">Ver. 29.</note> the <hi>wheate muſt be rooted up alſo;</hi> that is, a totall extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For indeed, if God ſhould at once deſtroy all wicked men, the very <hi>Compages or bands</hi> of humane ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety would in a moment be diſſolved. But we know the plucking up of many wicked ones, is a great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the <hi>growth of them who are good.</hi> So then what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever juſtice upon the Tares will help the increaſe and fruitfulneſſe of the wheate, that is not ſo much as ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at in this Parrble. And none but ſuch acts of juſtice are intended in this Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, for anſwer take that excellent rule, given <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>3</label> by a worthy Authour yet living. <hi>By the maine truths</hi> 
               <note place="margin">M. <hi>F Rom</hi> in his great Oracle.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>found in the whole Scripture, the ſingle and ſcattered places, which make ſome ſhew of diſproportion to the whole muſt be expounded and reſolved. Or if the way of reconciling them be doubtfull and difficult (as who can deny, but the infinite wiſedome of the Creator, may far exceed all the wiſedome of the creature) thoſe places may ſtand as ſecrets not underſtood; but they may not breake in peeces that body of truth, which we finde by joynts fitly and proportionably ioyned together in the body of Scripture.</hi> Seeing then the command of God, the practiſe of all good Kings, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, Miniſters and people, according to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall places, recorded in Scripture, are cleare, that evill perſons, as limited and explained, muſt not be borne. This or the like Texts may not be interpreted <hi>againſt them, but by them. One Scripture often expounds, but never contradicts another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The point carries in it, firſt a reproofe and convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> of thoſe who will by no meanes. <hi>beare the infirmities</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ro. 15 1.</note>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:64780:27"/> 
               <hi>of the weake,</hi> which in duty they ought, But can well enough beare <hi>the iniquity of the ſtrong,</hi> which in duty they ought not. If a tender conſcience did but ſcruple a <hi>Ceremony,</hi> or but ſtop (it may be) at ſome of their <hi>yeſter nights dreames,</hi> a late upſtart Innovation: Such were caſt in their opinion preſently (and it may be it would not be long before they heard on't) as perſons intolerable, as men not to be <hi>borne.</hi> But as for idle, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, blinde, covetous Shepheards, theſe were <hi>no bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to ſome,</hi> and too <hi>much borne by all.</hi> As for ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, drunkards, ſcoffers at that which is Religion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, prophaners of the Lords day, <hi>theſe were no bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,</hi> they were the companions or followers of ſome, and too <hi>much borne by all;</hi> even there, where they are the greateſt burden of all, <hi>at the Lords Table.</hi> As <note place="margin">Neh. 13. 24.</note> for <hi>profeſſed Papiſts,</hi> and ſuch as were <hi>Popiſhly affected,</hi> Who (like that impure off ſpring in <hi>Nehemiah) ſpake half in the ſpeech of</hi> Aſhdod, <hi>and could not ſpeake in the Iewes Language, but according to the Language of both people,</hi> theſe were <hi>no burdens to ſome, and too much borne by all the men of that Generation.</hi> Yea what diſcernable paines did ſome take to make them <hi>light enough for all to beare.</hi> Had not ſome ſtudied a complyance and accomodation with <hi>Rome?</hi> Had they not almoſt beaten out a <hi>middle way?</hi> which yet would have proved no better then that <hi>broad way</hi> which leads to the chambers of everlaſting death? What a cry was there by ſome for peace and unity? And why? Not that <hi>Ieruſalem might be a City</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 122. 3.</note> 
               <hi>compacted, or at unity within it ſelfe,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeakes (which ought to be not onely the prayer, but the earneſt endeavour of us all, and is one of the moſt deſireable and comely things in the world) But that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64780:27"/> 
               <hi>Ieruſalem and Babylon, Sion and Sodome, might be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and at unity one with another.</hi> Hence their blending of truth and errour, of ſuperſtition and holy worſhip. Hence their mincing and mangling our Doctrines and Tenets, and handling of controverſies as if they hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thornes, which they were afraid to touch. Hence their gentle dealing with errour, and ſpeaking Popery ſo faire. What could all this portend but a hope, yea a deſigne that at laſt unrighteouſneſſe and peace might embrace, that truth and a lye might kiſſe, that light and darkneſſe might mingle, that Chriſt might have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, whom our Fathers called Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt? and we beleeve he hath given us no cauſe to <hi>mend his Titles.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Surely that which was prophecied of <hi>Iſſachar</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to civill burdens, will be the Hiſtory of ſuch men in reference to ſpirituall, <hi>they crouched betweene two burdens, and bowed their conſciences to beare</hi> (and were angry with all that bowed not with them) poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly for <hi>Iſſachars</hi> reaſon too (though I judge no mans intentions) <hi>becauſe they ſaw that reſt was good, and the Land that it was pleaſant.</hi> Good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> once of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelfe to beare any burden of fine or ranſome, <note place="margin">2 Kin. 18. 14.</note> that he might purchaſe his peace with the King of old <hi>Babylon, I have offended</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>return from mee, that which thou putteſt upon me I will beare.</hi> We have cauſe to feare that ſome men have offered to beare much, and lay downe great prices for the purchaſe of peace, with the King of new <hi>Babylon.</hi> It is a good bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to buy truth with the expence of peace, but it is a miſerable, an undoing, a breaking bargaine, to buy peace with the expence or <hi>rendering up</hi> of any truth;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64780:28"/> though without queſtion peace is a <hi>richer commoditie</hi> then ſhould be <hi>bangled</hi> away upon <hi>trifeling niceties,</hi> or the <hi>crochets of Schoole-men.</hi> Such as are properly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Diſſidia Scholarum non Eccleſiarum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, this truth <hi>wipes off</hi> that falſe and <hi>ſcandalous</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>aſperſion</hi> which is ſo commonly caſt in the faces of the beſt: as if they were the people whom the Pſalmiſt <note place="margin">Pſ. 68, 30.</note> deſcribes, <hi>that delight in warre;</hi> as if they were all for <hi>troubled waters</hi> and the <hi>fire of contention,</hi> as if they were indeed like <hi>Solomons froward man that ſoweth ſtrife.</hi> Yea <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 28.</note> ſome will not feare to faſten that wickedneſſe upon them, which God by his Propher juſtly charges upon thoſe Hypocrites, <hi>Yee Faſt for ſtrife and debate,</hi> yee <note place="margin">Iſ. 58. 4.</note> pray for ſtrife, ye preach for ſtrife, ye conſult for ſtrife. And what is taken for the occaſion of all theſe hard ſpeeches, which ungodly ſinners (as S. <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeakes) <note place="margin">Iud. v. 15.</note> have ſpoken againſt them? Nothing but their anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableneſſe to the duty of this Text, <hi>They cannot beare</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Kin. 18. 17.</note> 
               <hi>them that are evill. Elijah</hi> was traduced for the <hi>Troubler of Iſrael,</hi> only becauſe he could not beare <hi>idolatrous Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Idol-worſhip.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>a man of ſtrife and a man of contention to the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>whole Earth.</hi> A man of ſtrife! there is much in that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. Chriſt was called a <hi>man of ſorrowes,</hi> to note the multitude of his ſorrowes, or as if he had bin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd <note place="margin">Iſa. 53. 3.</note> of all kinds and degrees of ſorrow. Antichriſt is called a <hi>man of ſinne,</hi> to note him, <hi>Merum ſcelus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2. 3</note> (as <hi>Beza</hi> gives the emphaſis of ſuch forms of ſpeaking) a man made up of wickedneſſe, or evill in the abſtract. So when <hi>Ieremy</hi> was called a man of ſtrife, it ſets him forth for a common Barretour, the verieſt wrangler in a Country. As if he were another <hi>Iſmael, his hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 16. 12.</note>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:64780:28"/> 
               <hi>every man, and every mans hand againſt him.</hi> And how got he this ſtile? Only becauſe he could not beare the prophaneneſſe of ſome, and the will-worſhip of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. His ſervice among the Iewes was in this ſence like that of <hi>Manlius Torquatus</hi> among the <hi>Romans,</hi> who gave it over, ſaying, <hi>Neither can I beare their manners, neither can they beare my government.</hi> The <hi>Iewes</hi> could not beare his plaine dealing and reproofes, neither could he beare their hypocriſie and rebellion. And <hi>Ieremy</hi> had almoſt beene like <hi>Manlius</hi> in giving over upon this ground, <hi>Then I ſaid I will not make mention of him, nor ſpeake any more in his name,</hi> Chap. 20. 9. <hi>But</hi> (he recovers himſelfe) <hi>his word was in mine heart, as a burning fire ſhut up in my bones, and I was weary with forbearing, and I could not ſtay.</hi> Heathens may, but beleevers cannot quite give up their worke, becauſe of the contradiction of ſinners. And hence he becomes a man of ſtrife. For in the cloſe of that verſe he ſhewes, that he had avoided all other occaſions, <hi>I</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 15. 10.</note> 
               <hi>have neither lent on uſury, nor men have lent to me on uſury,</hi> as if he had ſaid, I kept my ſelfe exactly within the bounds of my calling, I have not troubled my ſelf or this people with any other matters: I have not <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled my ſelfe</hi> in any of the affairs of this life, which <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 4.</note> he expreſſes by the <hi>Synecdoche</hi> of not <hi>lending upon uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and yet he was a man of contention.</hi> On the ſame termes we have many <hi>men of contention</hi> at this day. But as it was commanded <hi>Ieremy</hi> by the Lord in that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <note place="margin">ver. 19.</note> ſo may we ſay to theſe for all the clamours of men, <hi>Let them returne unto you, but doe not you returne unto them.</hi> For, doe they ſtrive againſt ſinne? It is their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Doe they oppoſe error? they are called to it. Doe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64780:29"/> they beat downe ſuperſtitious vanities? God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it: Can they not beare evill? It commends them to God: To agree with men thus were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire againſt Chriſt. Such peace on Earth is warre with Heaven. And we may anſwer all men, who would have us quiet with evill, as that Sword did to thoſe who ſaid unto it, <hi>O thou Sword of the Lord, how long</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 47. 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>will it be ere thou be quiet? put up thy ſelfe into thy ſcabbard, reſt and be ſtill. How can we be quiet, ſeeing the Lord hath given us a charge againſt</hi> Askelon, <hi>and againſt the Sea-ſhore</hi> (of <hi>Babylon) there he hath appointed us.</hi> He hath given all his people a charge againſt ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, againſt every evill, there hee hath appointed them. And may this Sword and Bow of all the upright in heart, be like the <hi>bow of</hi> Jonathan, <hi>and the Sword of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1. 22.</note> Saul, <hi>not turning backe nor returning empty, from the blood of ſinne-ſlaine, and from the fat of our mightieſt corruptions both in Church and Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me therefore cloſe this Doctrine with Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> to all, in your ſeverall places: beare not them that are evill; this <hi>impotency</hi> is your <hi>ſtrength</hi> for God, and this <hi>impatience</hi> your <hi>holineſse.</hi> Beare not evill in your Governments, in your Families, in your Children, in your Servants, in your friends that are as your owne ſoules, no, nor in your own ſouls.</p>
            <p>But let this word be to <hi>You eſpecially, even to You (of the Great and Honourable Aſſembly)</hi> who are the <hi>called of God and the King, and the choſen of this whole Nation. Your great worke for God, for the King, for the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is,</hi> to finde out and take away both things and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which are evill. Let your Acts teſtifie before Heaven and Earth, that <hi>you cannot beare them.</hi> It was
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64780:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:64780:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:64780:30"/> a noble reſolution of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who were no ſooner informed that their Brethren the children of <hi>Reuben</hi> and <note place="margin">Ioſh. 22. 11.</note> the children of <hi>Gad,</hi> and the halfe Tribe of <hi>Manaſseh, had built an Altar on the borders of Iordan:</hi> but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently they reſolve <hi>to fight againſt them.</hi> They will not <note place="margin">Ver. 12.</note> beare them in this, though their Brethren: the reaſon was, becauſe as the Morall Law taught <hi>but one God,</hi> ſo the Ceremoniall taught <hi>but one Altar;</hi> and therfore a ſecond was inſufferable. And had not their anſwer <note place="margin">V 13, 14. Ver. 21.</note> to the Princes (ſent in Embaſſie) ſatisfied them (that they meant it not for Sacrifice) doubtleſſe they had taken deepe revenge in that quarrell of God. And let me beſeech you this day to take up the like reſolution, and ſpeedily to execute it againſt every Altar, yea every thing about Gods worſhip, whoſe Authours and abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters cannot give as good an account for its <hi>beginning, ſtanding</hi> and <hi>continuance,</hi> as thoſe <hi>Reubenites</hi> did for that. I hope, I have ſeaſonably moved you this day of your Faſt to reſolve on this. For the Prophet tels us, this is Gods Faſt, <hi>Is not this the Faſt that I have</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 58. 6.</note> 
               <hi>choſen? To looſe the bands of wickedneſſe, to undoe the heavy burdens, and to let the oppreſſed goe free, and that yee breake every yoake?</hi> Thoſe things then, which are <hi>bands of wickedneſse,</hi> reſolve now to <hi>looſe them,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is a <hi>heavy burden</hi> reſolve to undoe it: when <note place="margin">1 King. 21 9, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. <hi>Iejunioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dies inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mebantur in reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liando Deo, maleficijs tollendu et jure dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Iunius in loc.</hi>
               </note> you are ſhewed <hi>any yoake that is not of Christs ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> reſolve as in the ſight of God this day, <hi>to breake it.</hi> That ſo all the <hi>bands being looſed,</hi> the <hi>burdens undone, the yoakes broken,</hi> every one that is oppreſſed <hi>may goe free.</hi> It was a cuſtome among the Iewes upon the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day of their Faſt to enquire after publike offenders. This was the reaſon why <hi>curſed Iezabel</hi> (to put a face
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64780:31"/> of holineſſe upon murder) cauſed a Faſt to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, that ſhe might ſlay <hi>innocent Naboath,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that he had <hi>blaſphemed God and the King.</hi> Change the perſons and the preſident in the maine is very imitable. It is a good part of a Faſt-duty, to judge thoſe to ſtoning (ſome legall puniſhment) who doe indeed <hi>caſt ſtones of blaſphemy either at God or Kings:</hi> And ſo in a proportion to judge any evill doer.</p>
            <p>Againe, I exhort to this the <hi>removing of evill</hi> as the moſt proper method of doing good. If the body na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall be diſtemper'd, it is to little purpoſe to be at the charge for <hi>Cordials and Reſtoratives,</hi> untill the <hi>noxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humours</hi> be <hi>purged and carried away.</hi> No man will bring in goodly furniture into his houſe untill the <hi>duſt and rubbiſh be ſwept up and caſt out.</hi> I doubt not your approbation (nay, who hath not ſeene your practiſe?) of this courſe for the reſtoring of the <hi>body politicke,</hi> and the <hi>Adorning of Gods houſe</hi> (his Church) <hi>whoſe houſe are we, even as many as hold fast the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 6.</note> 
               <hi>and rejoycing of the hope firme unto the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, I exhort to the removing of theſe bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, the evils of ſinne, leaſt wee provoke God to lay other burdens upon us, more (bleſſed be his name) then hee hath done yet of the evils of puniſhment; They that will beare the former burdens, <hi>ſhall beare</hi> the latter whether they will or no: <hi>Be they perſons or Nations.</hi> We have heard heretofore ſuch out-cryes againſt ſome faithfull Miniſters, as <hi>Amaziah</hi> made at Court, againſt <hi>Amos. The Land is not able to beare all their words.</hi> Wee have juſt cauſe to feare <note place="margin">Amos 7. 1.</note>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:64780:31"/> that the Land will not bee able long to beare all <hi>their workes,</hi> who made this cry: if <hi>they</hi> be borne. The burden of Gods wrath will ſinke a whole peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple together, who are willing to beare the errours and vanities of one another. At leaſt our children may beare the ſin of this generation, in bearing their ſin, as the children of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did their Fathers ſinne. Of whom God ſpeakes, <hi>(Numb.</hi> 14. 27.) <hi>How long ſhall I beare this Generation? Your carkaſſes ſhall fall in the Wilderneſse,</hi> v. 32. <hi>And your children ſhall wander in the wilderneſſe fourty yeares and beare your whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes:</hi> their Fathers dyed and they carried their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſinne fourty yeares, and were ſo long debarr'd the poſſeſſion of the promiſed <hi>Canaan.</hi> If we ſhould (as they) prove falſe to Chriſt, our carkaſſes may fall and our children may wander (who knowes how long) in a wilderneſſe of trouble and diſtraction, bearing this ſpirituall whoredome of ours, before they ſhall be admitted to the <hi>Canaan</hi> of a ſetled condition.</p>
            <p>Therfore (to conclude all) doe not this great, this dangerous evill, <hi>The Bearing of them that are, The Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of that which is evill. Beare not</hi> Oppreſſors and Merchants, rather then Stewards of Juſtice in the State. <hi>Beare not</hi> Buyers and Sellers, Money-changers rather then Miniſters in the Temple. <hi>Beare not</hi> the Seates of thoſe who have ſold and vext Doves, but have ſpared Crowes, and admitted uncleane birds to neſtle there. <hi>Beare not</hi> ignorant, idle, Idoll-Shepheards, who feed themſelves and not the flocke. <hi>Beare not</hi> ſonnes of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial,</hi> who make men abhorre the offerings of the Lord. <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 12 17.</note> 
               <hi>Beare not</hi> prophane Atheiſts, blaſphemous Swearers, ſwiniſh Drunkards, filthy Adulterers, bloudy Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64780:32"/> falſe Witneſſes in any corner of the Land: <hi>Beare not Idolaters, who change the truth of God into a Lye, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 25</note> 
               <hi>worſhip the creature more then the Creator (or the creature with the Creator) who is bleſſed for evermore: Beare not</hi> a Graven Image, nor the Maker, nor the Adorer of it; <hi>But defile all the Coverings of the Graven Images of Silver,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 30. 22.</note> 
               <hi>and the Ornaments of all the molten Images of Gold, caſt them away as a menstrous cloth, ſay unto them, with amigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty voice (a voice hath been heard as the voice of many wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters already) But ſay it now with a mighty voice, even the voice of a great thunder) Get ye hence. Beare not</hi> ſuperſtitious <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 2.</note> Innovators, who are all for mixtures in the worſhip of God: Whoſe minds are corrupted <hi>(and they have a mind to corrupt others) from the ſimplicity that is in Christ.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 3</note> The Goſpell and the wayes of it are not <hi>Simple,</hi> as <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity</hi> is oppoſed to depth of wiſedome <hi>(for therein is made knowne the manifold wiſedome of God)</hi> But as ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity <note place="margin">Eph. 3. 10.</note> is oppoſed to mixture: As in Philoſophy we diſtinguiſh between ſimple and mixt Bodies: ſo in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity we may between ſimple and mixt Ordinances. <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing the more ſimple</hi> (in this ſence) <hi>it is, the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent it is, and more free from corruption: And God who infinitely excels All, is most Simple: He is Ens Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciſſimum, Simplicity is his firſt Attribute.</hi> I heare, the Heralds have a rule amongſt them, That the moſt <hi>ſimple Bearing is</hi> the moſt <hi>honourable Bearing;</hi> Coates full of Devices ſhew a meane Deſcent. <hi>I am ſure the ſimpleſt Worſhip is fullest of Honour.</hi> A Religion full of devices could never, nor ever ſhall prove (it hath often attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to purchaſe) a Pedigree from Heaven. Then <hi>beare not</hi> mixing Innovators. <hi>Neither beare</hi> the old mixtures, the old Leaven which was left in the firſt reformation.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64780:32"/> 
               <hi>Take away the names of Baalim</hi> (the Remnants of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition) <hi>that they may no more be remembred by their Name.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 2. 17.</note> Conſider, and conſider whether you <hi>ſhould beare</hi> that, which hath been groaned to you as a burden, by many, by moſt Petitions from all the Quarters of the Land; I meane plainly, Our preſent Frame and Conſtitution of Church-Diſcipline and Government. But let this come to Tryall. Though <hi>Epheſus</hi> had not the patience to beare them or thoſe things which were evill; yet <hi>Epheſus</hi> had the patience to heare and try thoſe who ſaid they were good (though upon the debate it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared) they were not. <hi>Thou haſt tryed them which ſay they are Apoſtles and are not, and haſt found them Lyars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ſecond great worke ſpecified about which <note place="margin">Second worke of the Text.</note> that Church laboured and exerciſed their patience. And ſhould now be diſcuſſed, but I will onely hint at thoſe three particulars, which the words hold forth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſuch tryals.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The neceſſity of them. None either perſons or things, although they pretend divine Authority, ought to be admitted without tryall: For here, ſuch as ſaid <hi>they were Apoſtles were found Lyars.</hi> Who, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 8. 1 Cor. 13. 9. Mat. 24. 24 Acts 20. 29, 30. 2 Pet. 2. 1. 2 Cor. 18, 13, 14. Mat. 24 24</note> that all men by Nature <hi>are darkneſſe,</hi> and that the beſt are but in <hi>part enlightened:</hi> That Chriſt and his Apoſtles have prophecyed, <hi>Falſe Christs and falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles ſhall come,</hi> and that the worſt men ſhall come in the beſt ſhapes, <hi>A Devill will transforme himſelfe into an Angell of Light:</hi> That theſe <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> are many, and that they ſhall have <hi>many Followers,</hi> their Art being ſo exquiſite, that it will <hi>deceive (if it were poſſible) the very Elect:</hi> Who (I ſay) taking in theſe thoughts, will
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64780:33"/> not conclude the neceſſity of a Tryall, though <hi>Ius divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> be the plea.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the words hold forth the juſtice and equity of ſuch Tryals. Such as pretend divine Authority ought not to be rejected or condemned before Tryall. <hi>Thou haſt tryed them which ſay they are Apoſtles.</hi> It is moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable that ſo high and ſacred a plea as that ſhould be fully heard. Prejudices and ſuſpitions, bare reports and accuſations, miſcarriages and ill ſucceſſes cannot ſingle, or all together, beare out the rejection of any thing or perſon, before Tryall, which claimes by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the words hold forth the fruit and benefit of ſuch Tryals. Due tryall will quickly diſcover thoſe who are but pretenders, it will unmaske hypocrites: <hi>Thou (having tryed) haſt found them lyars.</hi> As the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace to mettall, or the Ballance to coyne, ſuch is due Tryall to men, it will ſhew what is Droſſe, what is Light. I ſay, due Tryall will ſhew it: For if you bring a light peece to a falſe beame, it will returne for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. <hi>Then it must be a due tryall;</hi> due for the Nature of it, not a <hi>Tryall of Curioſity,</hi> but of <hi>Sobriety,</hi> not of <hi>Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> but of <hi>Diſquiſition. Due alſo</hi> in regard of the <hi>Rule</hi> it is made by. <hi>Not by Tradition, not by Custome, not by Councels, not by that which is uſually called Antiquity:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 9. 4.</note> 
               <hi>The torne Garments, and mouldy bread of cunning</hi> Gibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onites, <hi>will not prove them come from the far countrey. Some things are ſo old that they are the worſe for it.</hi> Like the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites</hi> bread <hi>they mould:</hi> Truth doth not ſo. It is as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient as God, and (except the Law of Ceremonies) an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, as God is, who never waxeth old. <hi>Truth is old,</hi> but it <hi>waxeth not old;</hi> that which doth <hi>is ready to vaniſh</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:64780:33"/> 
               <hi>away:</hi> So the Apoſtle defines it. Such is the condition <note place="margin">Heb. 8. 13.</note> of things that waxe old, and ſuch will their Lot be, they <hi>muſt vaniſh.</hi> Whatſoever truth came from Heaven with Chriſt, ſhall never (in it ſelfe) feele decay. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever <hi>moulds now,</hi> though it be as old as the world, came but <hi>from our borders, This World: Heaven is the farre countrey.</hi> Therefore the tryall cannot be made by that which is uſually called Antiquity: But by that which tranſcends all humane Antiquity, Cuſtomes, Councels and Traditions (though all theſe may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute ſome help) <hi>The Word of God.</hi> That hath enough in <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 15, 17.</note> it <hi>to make the Man of God perfect;</hi> and what can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to perfection? That hath enough in it to make all men <hi>wiſe unto ſalvation.</hi> And what any man ſhould doe with wiſedome beyound that, I know not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> If any ſay, The Word of God is often the thing in Queſtion. The controverſie ariſeth about the ſence of a Text.</p>
            <p>I anſwer (with our learned writers againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts) the Scripture is both Text and gloſſe, and ever hath light in ſome place to cleare the darkeneſſe of any other.</p>
            <p>There is another rule of tryall given by Chriſt, which I will but touch alſo. <hi>By their fruits ye ſhall know them: doe men gather Grapes of Thornes, or Figs</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 16.</note> 
               <hi>of Thiſtles. The fruit of Apoſtleſhip</hi> was by paines in <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 13 c. 16. 5.</note> preaching of the Goſpell, and readineſſe to ſuffer for the Goſpell, to ſave ſoules. They cannot be Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call who preach not, or very ſeldome, and thoſe who would preach often they hinder. <hi>The fruits of Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Doctrines</hi> and Ordinances, are firſt the advancing of God <hi>in his free Grace,</hi> and the abaſing of man in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64780:34"/> of any <hi>Self-ſufficiency</hi> or <hi>Free-will.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom 14. 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the ſetling of unquiet conſciences, and the bringing in of aſſured peace into the ſoul.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>mortifying of luſts,</hi> and the <hi>perfecting of holineſse in the feare of God.</hi> Thoſe Doctrines or inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions about worſhip cannot be <hi>Apostolicall,</hi> which ſet up mans will, and leave his conſcience unſetled. Which give advantage to his Luſts, and leave his Graces un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſiſted.</p>
            <p>Doe but make ſerious tryall by theſe rules, and <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſaith it is, and is not Apoſtolicall, will be found a lye.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 13, 14, 15.</note> The benefit of ſuch a tryall is unſpeakeable, Truth will get more <hi>Luſtre,</hi> and we can loſe nothing but our <hi>droſſe,</hi> our <hi>hay and ſtubble;</hi> Our ſervices will find more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with God, and we ſhall have more ſatisfaction in our ſelves. And if after all your tryals you attaine not what you ought (Mans blindneſſe makes this too poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) yet this will be ſome anſwer, that you have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured what you can: Whereas not to try at all (as our caſe ſtands) were unanſwerable. What Apology can it beare, if (as <hi>Daniell</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>after all that is come upon us, we make not our prayer</hi> (and improve not our indeavour) <note place="margin">Dan 9. 13.</note> 
               <hi>that we might turne from our iniquities and underſtand his truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have but two admonitions in a few words from <note place="margin">Third part of the text</note> the third maine branch of this Text. Firſt, <hi>doe all theſe workes for Christs name ſake.</hi> Otherwiſe you may doe much good for others, but you ſhall get nothing (to purpoſe) by it your ſelves. <hi>Looke to your ends and aymes.</hi> They who built <hi>Babel</hi> did it to get <hi>themſelves a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen 11. 4.</note> 
               <hi>name;</hi> but they who will <hi>reſtore Ieruſalem</hi> muſt doe it <hi>to get Chriſt a name.</hi> If you labour and have patience,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64780:34"/> for Chriſt he is engag'd for your reward; if for your ſelves, Chriſt hath ſaid and almoſt ſworne it, <hi>Verily you have your reward.</hi> There is nothing more miſerable then to have our full pay in this world. And yet it is <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 2.</note> moſt certaine that no good we doe, will <hi>(redundare in perſonam)</hi> doe us good beyond (if it do ſo much) unleſſe we make God our end. <hi>Iehu</hi> had a worldly <note place="margin">2 Kin 9.</note> Kingdome for deſtroying <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts. The moſt wee can have is a worldly reward of honour, riches or great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for a good worke done for worldly ends, When ye have that ye have to the utmoſt worth of it. No man ever made more of ſuch a worke, or ever ſhall. If we ſeek our own glory, we ſhall never enter into Gods. It is a ſad thing to doe good with an ill heart.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to ſhut up all, doe and ſuffer all unto the end; let it be ſaid of you as of <hi>Epheſus, you have labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and have not fainted.</hi> Sincerity is ever accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with conſtancy. <hi>They who worke for right ends, will worke unto the end.</hi> They who ſeem what they are not <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nemo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtdiú per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonam fict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ferre, ficta citò in naturam ſuam reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt. Sen. Ep</hi> Heb. 6. 9. Gal. 6. 9. Rev. 3. 11.</note> will quickly (if they be put to it) ceaſe to be what they ſeeme. And they who worke by art only, will ſoone returne to their own nature. But (Honourable and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) <hi>I hope, nay I know better things of you,</hi> though I thus ſpeake: only I admoniſh you (with all humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) in the Apoſtles language, <hi>Be not weary in well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, for in due ſeaſon you ſhall reape, if you faint not.</hi> Or in the words of Chriſt to the <hi>Philadelphian Angell,</hi> hold faſt, let no man take your crowne. It is conſtancy which ſets the crowne upon the head of every action. If at any time any of your ſpirits begin to faint (as who may not have a qualme) then let me beſpeake ſuch a one as he Prophet doth <hi>almoſt fainting</hi> Iſrael. <hi>Hast thou</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 40. 18.</note>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:64780:35"/> 
               <hi>not knowne? Haſt thou not heard, that the everlaſting God, the Lord the Creatour of the ends of the Earth fainteth not, neither is weary.</hi> If you ſay, what's that to me? though God who is omnipotent faint not, yet I who am but weakeneſſe, may. No, while God hath ſtrength hee who workes for God cannot utterly want it. <hi>For</hi> (as it followes) <hi>He giveth power to the faint, and to them</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 29.</note> 
               <hi>that have no might, he increaſeth ſtrength. Even the youths ſhall faint and be weary, and the young men ſhall utterly fall</hi> (the greateſt ſtrength and vigour of naturall <note place="margin">Ver. 30.</note> abilities is weakneſſe and infirmity without God) <hi>But they who wait upon the Lord, ſhall renew their ſtrength,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ver. 31.</note> 
               <hi>they ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles; they ſhall run and not be weary, they ſhall walke and not faint.</hi> Chriſt who gives you worke, will alſo give you ſtrength. As it is your duty not to faint, ſo it is his promiſe that you ſhall not. <hi>What a Master doe we ſerve?</hi> who helps us <note place="margin">Ioh. 15. 3.</note> to do his buſineſſe, and then payes us for doing it, who workes ſo in us, as if we did nothing, and then rewards us ſo, as if we had done all. To him who gives all both ſtrength and reward, both Grace and Glory, be all ſtrength aſcribed and Glory given, for ever, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
